<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>A Singularity - Life</title><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/feeds/tag_life.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://arnavdhamija.com/</id><updated>2017-12-28T10:29:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Be The Opposite</title><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/be-the-opposite.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-12-28T10:29:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-12-28T10:29:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Arnav Dhamija</name></author><id>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2017-12-28:/blog/be-the-opposite.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;"The Opposite" (S05E21) was a watershed episode for Seinfeld. Not only did the series' direction change hands from Tom Cherones to Andy Ackerman after it, but the plots also became more focussed on the personality flaws in the characters rather than the bizarre situations they got themselves into. "The Opposite …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;"The Opposite" (S05E21) was a watershed episode for Seinfeld. Not only did the series' direction change hands from Tom Cherones to Andy Ackerman after it, but the plots also became more focussed on the personality flaws in the characters rather than the bizarre situations they got themselves into. "The Opposite" was probably the only episode in which these two tropes converged, making for something quite unlike any other Seinfeld episode. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that's not what I'm going to write about in this blog post. "The Opposite" has personal meaning for other reasons. As a short summary of the A-plot of this episode - George, a stout, balding, middle-aged man with no prospects with either a career or with the opposite sex, decides to act contrary to every instinct he's ever had. In a span of less than a day after doing so, he ends up with a new partner, a job with the New York Yankees, and finally gets the means to move out from his much beleaguered parents' house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though contrived for comical purposes, this episode holds something very profound under its veil of light-hearted comedy. The series goes to show that even when it's painfully obvious that you're clearly doing something wrong, it can be impossible to get out of the self-induced loop of listening to your instincts. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jerry also drives this home with an understatedly profound remark in this episode, &lt;em&gt;"If every instinct you have is wrong...then the opposite would have to be right!"&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="youtube youtube-16x9"&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/cKUvKE3bQlY" allowfullscreen seamless frameBorder="0"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it's a primal urge to follow your instincts, after all, your instincts are a product of your past experiences which have kept you alive. On the other hand, I feel a lot of it also has to do with getting into the comfort zone of being able to challenge your own perceptions. When you've been doing something wrong unconsciously, it becomes much harder to accept the fact that you were doing it wrong later on. Your brain accustoms itself to behaving in a certain way to a stimulus and left unchecked, this becomes a part of your personality. This is why I think shifting out of self-harmful behavior is so hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been a victim of falling to the trap of my own instincts ever since I joined college. Through a lot of time spent brooding and many moments of soul-searching through my daily diary entries, I was exactly aware of what I was unhappy with in life and what I had to do to fix it. Most of my problems could be traced down to a lack of self-esteem, but I was more than willing to wallow in pity than do anything about it. It was only a few months ago I decided to improve things by increasing physical activity and social exposure. There were many times I had a familiar nagging of doubt, but this too subsided as soon as I saw things &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; actually get better by &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; listening to yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a poignant quote I've saved from Anne Lammot's Bird by Bird about not listening to the radio station in your head - the radio station KFKD, or K-Fucked:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"If you are not careful, station KFKD will play in your head twenty-four hours a day, nonstop, in stereo. Out of the right speaker in your inner ear will come the endless stream of self-aggrandizement, the recitation of one’s specialness, of how much more open and gifted and brilliant and knowing and misunderstood and humble one is. Out of the left speaker will be the rap songs of self-loathing, the lists of all the things one doesn’t do well, of all the mistakes one has made today and over an entire lifetime, the doubt, the assertion that everything that one touches turns to shit, that one doesn’t do relationships well, that one is in every way a fraud, incapable of selfless love, that one has no talent or insight, and on and on and on. You might as well have heavy-metal music piped in through headphones while you’re trying to get your work done."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe the best way out lies in our mistakes, or rather, the opposite of them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Life"></category><category term="Misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Akademy 2017</title><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/akademy-2017.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-17T20:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-08-17T20:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Arnav Dhamija</name></author><id>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2017-08-17:/blog/akademy-2017.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last month, I attended KDE's annual conference, &lt;a href="https://akademy.kde.org/"&gt;Akademy 2017&lt;/a&gt;. This year, it was held in Almeria, a small Andalusian city on the south-east coast of Spain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The name of the conference is no misspelling, it's part of KDE's age old tradition of naming everything to do with KDE with a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last month, I attended KDE's annual conference, &lt;a href="https://akademy.kde.org/"&gt;Akademy 2017&lt;/a&gt;. This year, it was held in Almeria, a small Andalusian city on the south-east coast of Spain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The name of the conference is no misspelling, it's part of KDE's age old tradition of naming everything to do with KDE with a 'k'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a collection of amazing, life-changing experiences. It was my first solo trip abroad and it taught me so much about travel, KDE, and getting around a city with only a handful of broken phrases in the local language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Travel&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My trip began from the recently renamed Kempegowda International Airport, Bangalore. Though the airport is small for an international airport, the small size of the airport works to its advantage as it is very easy to get around. Check-in and immigration was a breeze and I had a couple of hours to check out the loyalty card lounge, where I sipped soda water thinking about what the next seven days had in store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first leg of my trip was on a Etihad A320 to Abu Dhabi, a four hour flight departing at 2210 on 20 July. The A320 isn't particularly unique equipment, but then again, it was a rather short leg. The crew onboard that flight seemed to be a mix of Asian and European staff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economy class in Etihad was &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; better than any other Economy class product I'd seen before. Ample legroom, very clean and comfortable seats, and an excellent IFE system. I was content looking at the HUD-style map visualisation which showed the AoA, vertical speed, and airspeed of the airplane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the way, I scribbled a quick diary entry and started reading part 1 of Sanderson's Stormlight Archive - 'The Way of Kings'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Descent to Abu Dhabi airport started about 3:30 into the flight. Amber city lights illuminated the desert night sky. Even though it was past midnight, the plane's IFE reported an outside temperature of 35C. Disembarking from the plane, the muggy atmosphere hit me after spending four hours in an air-conditioned composite tube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The airport was dominated by Etihad aircraft - mainly Airbus A330s, Boeing 787-8s, and Boeing 777-300ERs. There were also a number of other airlines part of the Etihad Airways Partners Alliance such as Alitalia, Jet Airways, and some Air Berlin equipment. As it was a relatively tight connection, I didn't stop to admire the birds for too long. I traversed a long terminal to reach the boarding gate for the connecting flight to Madrid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flight to Madrid was another Etihad operated flight, only this time on the A320's larger brethren - the A330-200. This plane was markedly older than the A320 I had been on the first leg of the trip. Fortunately, I got the port side window seat in a 2-5-2 configuration. The plane had a long take-off roll and took off a few minutes after 2am. Once we reached cruising altitude, I opened the window shade. The clear night sky was full of stars and I must have spent at least five minutes with my face glued to the window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried to sleep, preparing myself for the long day ahead. Soon after waking up, the plane landed at Madrid Barajas Airport and taxied for nearly &lt;em&gt;half-an-hour&lt;/em&gt; to reach the terminal. After clearing immigration, I picked up my suitcase and waited for a bus which would take me to my next stop - the Madrid Atocha Railway Station. Located in the heart of city, the Atocha station is one of Madrid's largest train stations and connects it to the rest of Spain. My train to Almeria was later that day - at 3:15 in the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On reaching Atocha, I got my first good look at Madrid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170721_094946172.jpg"&gt;     &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My facial expression was quite similar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170721_114110394.jpg"&gt;          &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was struck by how orderly everything was, starting with the traffic. Cars gave the right of way to pedestrians. People walked on zebra crossings and cyclists stuck to the defined cycling lanes. A trivial detail, but it was a world apart from Bangalore. Shining examples of Baroque and Gothic architecture were scattered among newer establishments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a few hours to kill before I had to catch my train, I roamed around Buen Retiro Park, one of Spain's largest public parks. It was a beautiful day, bright and sunny with the warmth balanced out by a light breeze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My heavy suitcase compelled me to walk slowly which let me take in as much as I could. Retiro Park is a popular stomping ground for joggers, skaters, and cyclists alike. Despite it being 11am on a weekday, I saw plenty of people jogging though the park. After this, I trudged through some quaint cobbled neighbourhoods with narrow roads and old apartment buildings dotted with small shops on the ground floor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it was the sleep-deprivation or dehydration after a long flight, but everything felt so surreal! I had to pinch myself a few times - to believe that I had come thousands of miles from home and was actually travelling on my own in a foreign land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I returned to Atocha and waited for my train. By this time, I came to realise that language was going to be a problem for this trip as very few people spoke English and my Spanish was limited to a few basic phrases - notably 'No hables Espanol' and 'Buenos Dias' :P Nevertheless, the kind folks at the station helped me find the train platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trains in Spain are operated by state-owned train companies. In my case, I would be travelling on a Renfe train going till Almeria. The coaches are arranged in a 2-2 seating configuration, quite similar to those in airplanes, albeit with more legroom and charging ports. The speed of these trains is comparable to fast trains in India, with a top speed of about 160km/hr. The 700km journey was scheduled to take about 7 hours. There was plenty of scenery on the way with sloping mountain ranges and deserted valleys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170721_210241975.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Big windows encouraged sightseeing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After seven hours, I reached the Almeria railway station at 10pm. According to Google Maps, the hostel which KDE had booked for all the attendees was only 800m away - well within walking distance. However, unbeknownst to me, I started walking in the opposite direction (my phone doesn't have a compass!). This kept increasing the Google Maps ETA and only when I was 2km off track I realised something was very wrong. Fortunately, I managed to get a taxi to take me to Residencia Civitas - a university hostel where all the Akademy attendees would be staying for the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After checking in to Civitas, I made my way to the double room. Judging from the baggage and the shoes in the corner, someone had moved in here before I did. About half an hour later, I found out who - &lt;a href="https://github.com/rahulyadav170923"&gt;Rahul Yadav&lt;/a&gt;, a fourth year student at DTU, Delhi. Exhausted after an eventful day of travel, I switched off the lights and went to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Conference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day, I got to see other the Akademy attendees over breakfast at Civitas. In all, there were about 60-70 attendees, which I was told was slightly smaller than previous years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conference was held at University of Almería, located a few kilometres from the hostel. KDE had hired a public bus for transport to and from the hostel for all the days of the conference. The University was a stone's throw from the Andalusian coastline. After being seated in one of the larger lecture halls, Akademy 2017 was underway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170722_135420112.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Konqi! And KDE Neon!&lt;/em&gt;    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The keynote talk was by Robert Kayne of Metabrainz, about the story of how MusicBrainz was formed out of the ashes of CDDB. The talk set the tone for the first day of Akademy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee break after the first two talks was much needed. I was grappling with sleep deprivation and jet lag from the last two days and needed all the caffeine and sugar I could get to keep myself going for the rest of the day. Over coffee, I caught up with some KDE developers I met at QtCon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the day, there were a lot of good talks, notably 'A bit on functional programming', and five quick lightning talks on a variety of topics. Soon after this, it was time for my very own talk - &lt;a href="https://conf.kde.org/en/akademy2017/public/events/337"&gt;'An Introduction to the KIO Library'&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- The KIO Library is a neat abstraction used by many applications. It allows applications to access data from a wide variety of local and network protocols without having to implement special code to handle the aforementioned protocol. This makes it easy to add file management capabilities in KDE applications and the API is used extensively in Dolphin. --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The audience for my talk consisted of developers with several times my experience. Much to my delight, the &lt;em&gt;maintainer&lt;/em&gt; of the KIO Library, David Faure was in the audience as well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's where I learned another thing about giving presentations - they never quite go as well as it seems to go when rehearsed alone. I ended up speaking faster than I planned to, leaving more than enough time for a QA round. Just as I was wary about, I was asked some questions about the low-level implementation of KIO which thankfully David fielded for me. I was perspiring after the presentation, and it wasn't the temperature which was the problem 😅 A thumbs up from David afterwards gave me some confidence that I had done alright.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following this, I enjoyed David Edmundson's talk about Binding properties in QML. The next presentation I attended after this is where things ended up getting heated. Paul Brown went into detail about everything wrong with &lt;a href="https://techbase.kde.org/Kirigami"&gt;Kirigami's TechBase&lt;/a&gt; page. This drew some, for lack of a better word, passionate people to retaliate. Though it was it was only supposed to be a 10 minute lightning talk, the debate raged on for half-an-hour among the two schools of thought of how TechBase documentation should be written. The only thing which brought the discussion to an end was the bus for returning to Civitas leaving sharp at 8pm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still having a bit of energy left after the conference, I was ready to explore this Andalusian city. One thing which worked out nicely on this trip is the late sunset in Spain around this time of the year. It is as bright as day even at around 9pm and the light only starts waning at around 930pm. This gave Rahul and me plenty of time to head to the beach, which was about a 20 minute walk from the hostel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, it struck me how much I loved the way of life here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike Madrid, Almeria is not a known as a tourist destination so most of the people living there were locals. In a span of about half an hour I watched how an evening unfolds in this city. As the sun started dipping below the horizon, families with kids, college couples, and high-school friends trickled from the beach to the boardwalk for dinner. A typical evening looked delightfully simple and laid-back in this peaceful city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The boardwalk had plenty of variety on offer - from seafood to Italian cuisine. One place caught my eye, a small cafe with Doner Kebab called 'Taj Mahal'. After a couple of days of eating nothing but bland sandwiches, Rahul and I were game for anything with a hint of spice of it. As I had done in Madrid, I tried ordering Doner Kebab using a mixture of broken Spanish and improvised sign language, only to receive a reply from the owner in Hindi! It turned out that the owner of the restaurant was Pakistani and had migrated to Spain seven years ago. Rahul made a point to ask for more chilli - and the Doner kebabs we got were not lacking in spice. I had more chilli in that one kebab than I normally would have had in a week. At least it was a change from Spanish food, which I wasn't all that fond of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170722_210643404.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;View from the boardwalk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170723_212852615.jpg"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day was similar to the first, only a lot more fun. I spent a lot amount of time interacting with the people from KDE India. I also got to know my GSoC mentor, &lt;a href="https://blog.baloneygeek.com/"&gt;Boudhayan Gupta&lt;/a&gt; (@BaloneyGeek). The talks for this day were as good as the ones yesterday and I got to learn about Neon Docker images, the story behind KDE's Slimbook laptop, and things to look forward to in C++17/20.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talks were wrapped up with the Akademy Awards 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170723_171825707.jpg"&gt;           &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;David Faure and Kevin Ottens&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were still 3 hours of sunlight left after the conference and not being ones to waste it, we headed straight for the beach. Boudhayan and I made a treacherous excursion out to a rocky pier covered with moss and glistening with seawater. My well-worn sandels were the only thing keeping me from slipping onto a bunch of sharply angled stones jutting out from the waves. Against my better judgement, I managed to reach the end of the pier only to see a couple of crabs take interest in us. With the tide rising and the sun falling, we couldn't afford to stay much longer so we headed back to the beach just as we came. Not long after, I couldn't help myself and I headed into the water with enthusiasm I had only knew as a child. Probably more so for BaloneyGeek though, who headed in headfirst with his three-week-old Moto G5+ in his pocket (Spoiler: the phone was irrevocably damaged from half a minute of being immersed in saltwater). In the midst of this, we found a bunch of KDE folks hanging out on the beach with several boxes of pizza and bottles of beer. Free food!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exhausted but exhilarated, we headed back to Civitas to end another very memorable day in Almeria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170723_212706271.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Estacion Intermodal, a hub for public transport in Almeria&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the talks completed, Akademy 2017 moved on to its second leg, which consisted more of BoFs (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Birds_of_a_feather_(computing)"&gt;Birds of a Feather&lt;/a&gt;) and workshops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The QML workshop organised by Anu was timely as my relationship with QML has been hot and cold. I would always go in circles with the QML Getting Started tutorials as there aren't as many examples of how to use QtQuick 2.x as there are with say, Qt Widgets. I understood how to integrate JavaScript with the QML GUI and I will probably get around to making a project with the toolkit when I get the time. Paul Brown held a BoF about writing good user documentation and deconstructed some more pretentious descriptions of software with suggestions on how to avoid falling into the same pitfalls. I sat on a few more BoFs after this, but most of the things went over my head as I wasn't contributing to the projects discussed there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feeling a bit weary of the beach, Rahul and I decided to explore the inner parts of the city instead. We planned to go to the Alcazaba of Almeria, a thousand-year-old fortress in the city. On the way, we found a small froyo shop and ordered a scoop with chocolate sauce and lemon sauce. Best couple of euros spent ever! I loved the tart flavour of the froyo and how it complemented the toppings with its texture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gastronomic digression aside, we scaled a part of the fort only to find it locked off with a massive iron door. I got the impression that the fort was rarely ever open to begin with. With darkness fast approaching, we found ourselves in a dodgy neighbourhood and we tried to get out as fast as we could without drawing too much attention to ourselves. This brought an end to my fourth night in Almeria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170724_213148815_BURST001.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;View from Alcazaba&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The BoFs continued throughout the 25&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, the last full day of Akademy 2017. I participated in the GSoC BoF where KDE's plans for future GSoCs, SoKs, and GCIs were discussed (isn't that a lot of acronyms!). Finally, this was one topic where I could contribute to the discussion. If there was any takeaway from the discussion for GSoC aspirants, it is to start as early as you can!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sat on some other BoFs as well, but most of the discussed topics were out of my scope. The Mycroft and VDG BoF did have some interesting exchange of ideas for future projects that I might consider working on if I get &lt;em&gt;free&lt;/em&gt; time in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rahul was out in the city that day, so I had the evening to explore Almeria all by myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I fired up Google Maps to see anything of interest nearby. To the west of the hostel was a canal I hadn't seen previously so I thought it would be worth a trip. Unfortunately, because of my poor navigation skills and phone's lack of compass, I ended up circling a flyover for a while before ditching the plan. I decided to go to the beach as a reference point and explore from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What was supposed to be a reference point ended up becoming the destination. There was still plenty of sunlight and the water wasn't too cold. I put one toe in the water, and then a foot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, I &lt;em&gt;ran&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running barefoot alone the coastline was one of the best memories I have of the trip. For once, I didn't think twice about what I was doing. It was pure liberation. I didn't feel the exertion or the pebbles pounding my feet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170725_205642101.jpg"&gt;           &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Almeria's Beaches&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end of the coastline had a small fort and a dirt trail which I would've very much wanted to cycle on. After watching the sun sink into the sea, I ran till the other end of the boardwalk to find an Italian restaurant with &lt;strong&gt;vegetarian&lt;/strong&gt; spinach spaghetti. Served with a piece of freshly baked bread, dinner was delicious and capped off yet another amazing day in Almeria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170725_222250909.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dinner time!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Day Trip&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 26&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; was the final day of the conference. Unlike the other days, the conference was only for half a day with the rest of the day kept aside for a day trip. I cannot comment on how the conference went on this day as I had to rush back to the hostel to retrieve my passport, which was necessary to attend the day trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right around 2 in the afternoon we boarded the bus for the day trip. Our first stop was the Plataforma Solar de Almería, a solar energy research plant in Almeria. It houses some large heliostats for focussing sunlight at a point on a tower. This can be used for heating water and producing electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was another facility used for testing the tolerance of spacecraft heat shields by subjecting them to temperatures in excess of 2000C by focussing sunlight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170726_152443372.jpg"&gt;           &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Heliostats focus at the top of the tower&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next stop was at the San José village. Though not too far from Almeria, the village is frequented by tourists much more than Almeria is and has a very different vibe. The village is known for its beaches, pristine clear waters, and white buildings. I was told that the village was used in the shooting of some films such as The Good, The Bad, and The Ugly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170726_173502801.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our final stop for the day was at the Rodalquilar Gold Mine. Lost to time, the mine had been shut down in 1966 due to the environmental hazards of using cyanide in the process to sediment gold. The mine wouldn't have looked out of place in a video-game or an action movie, and indeed, it was used in the filming of Indiana Jones and the Last Crusade. There was a short trek from the base of the mine to a trail which wrapped around a hill. After descending from the top we headed back to the hostel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170726_190645909.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This concluded my stay in Almeria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Madrid&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After checking out of the hostel early the next morning, I caught a train to Madrid. I had a day in the city before my flight to Bangalore the next day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reached Atocha at about 2 in the afternoon and checked in to a hotel. I spent the entire evening exploring Madrid on foot and an electric bicycle through the BiciMAD rental service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Photo Dump&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170727_070806970.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170727_142622000.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170727_161202727.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170727_163629143.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170727_170914992.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170727_173745292.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170727_184840175.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170727_190420712.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170727_194115723.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170727_194935333.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170727_202014639.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170727_205415016.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Return&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My flight back home was on the following morning, on the 28 July. The first leg of the return was yet again, on an Etihad aircraft bound for Abu Dhabi. This time it was an A330-300. It was an emotional 8 hour long flight - with the memories of Akademy still fresh in my mind. To top it off, I finished &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EarthBound"&gt;EarthBound&lt;/a&gt; (excellent game!) during the flight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Descent into Abu Dhabi started about half an hour before landing. This time though, I got to see the bizarre Terminal 1 dome of the Abu Dhabi airport. The Middle East has always been a mystical place for me. The prices of food and drink in the terminal were hard to stomach - 500mL of water was an outrageous 8 UAE Dirhams (₹140)! Thankfully it wasn't a very long layover, so I didn't have to spend too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/akademy2017/resized/IMG_20170728_180441863.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note to self: may cause tripping if stared at for too long&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next leg was a direct flight to Bangalore, on another Etihad A330. Compared to all the travel I had done in the last two days, the four hour flight almost felt too short. I managed to finish 'Your Lie in April' on this leg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had mixed emotions on landing in Bangalore - I was glad to have reached home, but a bit sad that I had to return to college in only two days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Akademy 2017 was an amazing trip and I am very grateful to KDE for letting me present at Akademy and for giving me the means of reaching there. I hope I can make more trips like these in the future!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="KDE"></category><category term="Life"></category><category term="Travel"></category></entry><entry><title>On College Students</title><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/on-college-students.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-07-20T20:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-07-20T20:30:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Arnav Dhamija</name></author><id>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2017-07-20:/blog/on-college-students.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As a school kid, I was always fascinated by meeting college students from top tier colleges. There was something surreal in the way they talked and they confidently stood with T-shirts proudly proclaiming the name of their alma mater. I used to have the impression that no matter what came …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As a school kid, I was always fascinated by meeting college students from top tier colleges. There was something surreal in the way they talked and they confidently stood with T-shirts proudly proclaiming the name of their alma mater. I used to have the impression that no matter what came in the future, there was a certain justification of their abilities and intelligence. Perhaps society had conditioned me to think as such. Maybe their apparent confidence was a just a projection of how I thought it would feel to be in a top tier college.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It struck me just recently that everyone in my college is of the same surreal breed I used to look upto. But now, the magic is lost on me. It's no longer the case that simply being admitted to a Tier-1 college would give one opportunities otherwise impossible. At the same time, the name of the college on your degree matters little if you haven't done enough legwork in college to justify being called an "Engineer".&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Life"></category><category term="College"></category></entry><entry><title>What I've been upto</title><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/this-semester-has-gone-little-too-fast.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-19T11:09:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-12-19T11:09:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Arnav Dhamija</name></author><id>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2016-12-19:/blog/this-semester-has-gone-little-too-fast.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This semester has gone a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; too fast for my liking. Though there were
plenty of good memories and takeaways from this semester, it has been by far
my most stressful time in this college yet. Between taking on a number of
technical projects and trying to rescue a sharply …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This semester has gone a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; too fast for my liking. Though there were
plenty of good memories and takeaways from this semester, it has been by far
my most stressful time in this college yet. Between taking on a number of
technical projects and trying to rescue a sharply falling SG due to a poor T1,
there has been very little free time this sem. Above all, this sem has shown
me just how limited of a resource brain power is. Thinking about solving
problems wears me out much more easily than it used to.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's not to say what I've been doing is all drudgery. Some interesting
projects that I've been working on:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;GSoC 2016 Project - kio-stash&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yup, this &lt;a href="https://github.com/KDE/kio-stash"&gt;project&lt;/a&gt; has been in the pipeline
for months. While it (mostly) works on a clean install of KDE, it has some
bugs with copying with mtp:/ device slaves and isn't very well integrated with
Dolphin yet. It is in my best interest to have this shipped with KDE
Frameworks as soon as possible, so I'm looking into patching Dolphin with
better, more specific action support for my project.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;IEEE Signal Processing Cup 2017 - Real-Time Beat Tracking Challenge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The premise of this project doesn't seem very complicated - a team just needs
to submit an algorithm which can successfully detect the beats in a song in
real-time on an embedded device. Heck, I had already implemented the same on
an Arduino with a microphone for rather &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lMb1XScNgOs"&gt;fancy lighting in my hostel
room&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately, as I've
learned the hard way, anything that looks simple is deceptive and this project
is a perfect example. For one thing, a song by itself in the amplitude-time
domain is nearly impossible to extract any data from, so it requires a (Fast)
Fourier Transform to extract frequency bin amplitudes to get anything useful
from it. Next, obtaining beat onset and detection requires generating a
tempogram to find the BPM of a song to find the approximate beat positions.
There are many interesting approaches and different algorithms to solve this
problem. Fortunately, I'm not doing this alone and the seniors I'm working
with have a better understanding of the more difficult mathematical components
of this project, leaving me free to code in C++ and deploy it on actual
hardware.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;foss@bphc&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is a society on campus I started with
&lt;a href="https://github.com/aero31aero/"&gt;three&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://github.com/TestSubjector"&gt;programmers&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://github.com/Nischay-
Pro/"&gt;far&lt;/a&gt; more competent than myself. It all started in September this year
when we had the two-day long &lt;a href="https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Hackathon_BPHC"&gt;Wikimedia
Hackathon&lt;/a&gt; on campus.
Though my contribution to Wikimedia was small, I got a lot out of the
hackathon by meeting the people from Amrita University who came for organising
the event. Listening to what
&lt;a href="https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/User:01tonythomas"&gt;Tony&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="http://srijanagarwal.me/"&gt;Srijan&lt;/a&gt; had to say about how much working for
foss@amrita had benefited them made me realise how much room for improvement
there was in BPHC. As far as this society goes, things are still in their
infancy, yet I feel there is just enough critical mass of talent and
enthusiasm in open source development to push this society forward. We even
have our own
&lt;a href="https://fossbphc.github.io/docs/constitution.html"&gt;Constitution&lt;/a&gt;!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Making a personal website?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Blogspot has been a faithful home for this blog for over half a decade,
it is time to move to a modern solution for hosting. Plus setting up a website
will teach me a bit about web development too, and I've needed an excuse to
learn it for a while. Surely it can't be all that hard, right?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Burnout&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the slew of all these technical projects seemed like a good idea at the
time, it has pushed me closer to burning out. It is the same feeling as what I
felt the same time last year, albeit for different reasons.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of it has carried over from studying harder at the end of this sem than I
had done so before. To my surprise, studying under pressure was actually more
effective than it was without. In some ways, it was a throwback to studying
for the number of exams nearly a couple of years ago. It has made me question
whether any of my education was as much for the knowledge as it was for the
desperation of avoiding failure. I still haven't figured it out, but at least
I feel like I'm not as adverse to putting in the hours for getting a decent
CGPA as I had been last semester.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been compromises in other spheres of college life as well,
investing so much time in studying or doing projects has made me cut down my
participation in other clubs and I've quit nearly all the non-technical clubs
I joined last year. There's more than that too - I feel it's much harder to be
fully immersed in anything anymore.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it's just something else which requires more soul searching.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="College"></category><category term="Life"></category><category term="KDE"></category></entry><entry><title>What do I do now?</title><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/what-do-i-do-now.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-04-14T01:38:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-04-14T01:38:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Arnav Dhamija</name></author><id>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2016-04-14:/blog/what-do-i-do-now.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I spend a lot of time thinking since I've joined college.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had postponed a lot of introspection during the two years I spent slogging
away for the JEE. But now, with ample free time and practically no requirement
to go to classes, I've finally got some time to look …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I spend a lot of time thinking since I've joined college.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had postponed a lot of introspection during the two years I spent slogging
away for the JEE. But now, with ample free time and practically no requirement
to go to classes, I've finally got some time to look back and see how things
have turned out. College started off on the back foot, and while 1-1 had its
charms, I wasn't exactly happy about how things had turned out at the time due
to a bad time with the &lt;a href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/t2-years-and-counting-iit-jee.html#entrancexams"&gt;entrance exams&lt;/a&gt; for all the
&lt;a href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/t2-years-and-counting-iit-jee.html#bitsat"&gt;wrong&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/t2-years-and-counting-iit-jee.html#screwup0"&gt;reasons&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I digress, as time has passed, I have learned to live with my failure a
little better every day, though it still sticks out like a sore thumb on an
otherwise decent academic profile. Despite this, it has been an interesting
exercise is to compare what I expected from college a year ago and reality.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, BITS Pilani (this applies to all campuses, but in this case,
Hyderabad Campus) has some of best internal systems among &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; Indian
colleges. Optional attendance, good grading system, decent infrastructure, and
a lot of freedom is more than what can be asked for in a lot of other colleges.
Despite some glaring flaws such as the lack of a solid technical culture, this
college has punched above its weight for a new institution.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as an engineering utopia? I feel like we are way short of the mark &lt;a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/technology/technology/2013/02/aaron_swartz_he_wanted_to_save_the_world_why_couldn_t_he_save_himself.html"&gt;Aaron&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9vz06QO3UkQ&amp;amp;nohtml5=False"&gt;Swartz&lt;/a&gt; mentioned
in his &lt;a href="http://www.aaronsw.com/weblog/visitingmit"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Perhaps it’s natural, when doing something so greedy and practical as a
startup, to pine for the idealized world of academia. Its image as a place in
an idyllic location filled with smart people has always been attractive; even
more so with the sense that by being there one can get smarter simply through
osmosis. People describe a place of continual geekiness, of throwing chemicals
into the river and building robots in free time. A magical place for hackers
to just enjoy themselves."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This aside, I am of the opinion that the version of me a year ago would have
been sorely disappointed by the version of me today. I feel that I was &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt;
more hardworking and efficient back at that time. The two years in JEE
preparation were undoubtedly the worst years of my school life but now looking
back, those dark days brought out the best in me in the briefest of
moments. Had I not prepared for JEE at all, I would have had no idea just how driven and hard-working I could be
for a goal that would always be just a touch out of view.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite my frustrations with life during JEE preparation, the epiphanies I
used to have on weekly basis with studying physics kept me going.
It was a positive feedback loop with no goading required. On the other hand I
can't remember the last time I actually enjoyed learning something in class in
this college. I hope it isn't a sign of things to come when I start
"engineering" coursework in my second year but as of now, I have pretty much lost all
motivation to study.  The unbridled enthusiasm I used to have when studying
for the entrance exams and the giddy thoughts of making batshit crazy projects in
college has dwindled. In my first semester, it was a convenient excuse to
blame this on burnout after pushing my limits for two years but I've come to
realize that the reason is probably shallower than that. It's not just with
academics though - wasting time &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; feels painful but I have nothing I
want to do to fill in the gaps. Is there a cause for this? Probably. Have I
figured it out? Absolutely not.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels like an artificial conflict of time between these misguided academic
pursuits and to actually work on something worthwhile. I could put up with
it in school with the thought that there would be enough free time to pursue
this in college - and while there is - it begs the question why such
artificial restraints on time in the form of exams are always looming in the
first place.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point of time, I don't know what to do. With compre in half a month
but a &lt;a href="https://goo.gl/BYOWdG"&gt;GSoC project&lt;/a&gt; and a couple other projects I've
planned in the pipeline, it's a pretty easy decision to make the choice of
which one of these two things I would want to work on. For a CGPA for which I
cannot care for anymore, it might be one of the worst decisions I can make.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Rants"></category><category term="College"></category><category term="Life"></category></entry><entry><title>T+2 Years And Counting: My IIT-JEE preparation story</title><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/t2-years-and-counting-iit-jee.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-06-17T10:29:00+05:30</published><updated>2015-06-17T10:29:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Arnav Dhamija</name></author><id>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2015-06-17:/blog/t2-years-and-counting-iit-jee.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As the title indicates, it's been a while since I've written anything here. I
don't know if anyone still reads this blog, but I sure appreciate if you do!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I guess some explanation is due here - it's been a combination of my lack
of cohesive thought and lack of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As the title indicates, it's been a while since I've written anything here. I
don't know if anyone still reads this blog, but I sure appreciate if you do!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I guess some explanation is due here - it's been a combination of my lack
of cohesive thought and lack of motivation to publish anything. Part of the
reason is also that I've given a shot at the IIT-JEE which is something that
I've wanted to write about for a while.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the uninitiated, the IIT-JEE is an entrance exam for the IITs which are
regarded by some as the best engineering colleges in India. The exam is held
at the end of 12th grade annually. Hundreds of thousands attempt the exam.
Tens of thousands slog away countless hours of their last few years in high
school preparing for it. Only a few hundred actually succeed.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many with some strong aspirations of becoming an engineer, I stumbled
upon this path a couple of years ago. I loved making/breaking things and had
(what I felt) a keen interest in science, so it was a natural option for me to
take some engineering related field over other options. I loved airplanes too
and I would spend many happy hours on Wikipedia reading up about the Concorde
(gorgeous plane), the XB-70, their engines, their airframe designs, and the
engineers behind it all. I was fiercely determined to enter the aviation
industry as an aerospace engineer to create a revolutionary aircraft on the
lines of the Concorde.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's an unspoken reality that one's chances at IIT-JEE significantly decrease
without the assistance of extra classes outside school, also known as coaching
classes. I joined one at the start of the summer vacation prior to 11th called
FIITJEE after getting a decent fee waiver via their admission test. I was no
stranger to horror stories of 11th and 12th grade for school students, but I
felt things would change for the better after the brain-numbing syllabus of
10th grade.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it did. To an extent. Things passed very quickly through the first few
months of FIITJEE where I was tirelessly trying to understand every fragment
of information that would probably help in making it through with a good rank
in IIT Advance. My math wasn't strongest to begin with and I trudged along
with chem with ambivalence to the subject material. Studying physics, both in
class and at home was amazing. Thanks to our FIITJEE physics teacher, one of
the best teachers I've ever had, physics by acompared long shot became my
favorite subject for the next two years. It always just clicked and moreover
studying physics and learning something new to solve an interesting problem
was just &lt;em&gt;fun&lt;/em&gt;. I remember physics and chemistry (primarily physics) passing
along with relative smoothness but it felt like I was banging my head on a
brick wall with math. This led to the vicious cycle of frustration, studying
to remedy my weaknesses followed by more frustration when things didn't seem
to be getting better. Despite all the apathy towards math I still managed to
get through reasonably well with a consistent 2nd place in the phase tests and
three digit ranks in the FIITJEE AIiTS. Unfortunately my reckless, unplanned
approach towards studying in the first few months cost me greatly in other
spheres of life and I was not a happy person to be around.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was around this point in time when I felt things slipping - yes, decent
ranks in the phase tests were welcome but did it actually mean anything in
such a sample set? There was also a storm brewing on the horizon - in the form
of organic chemistry. Hard as I tried, I could never commit the material to
memory. My woes with organic chem were exemplified with a jaw-dropping 11/25
in a school UT...which meant I had spent about 2 hours studying for every mark
earned in that test :P  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately things slowly shaped up to look better right after 11th grade.
Thanks to some quality teaching at FIITJEE and a lot time with chem textbooks
organic chem started to become clearer for me. Shortly thereafter I managed to
top Bangalore in FIITJEE's classroom program in the organic chem phase test.
Of all the times I've had to bounce back from a tight situation in those 2
years, this was probably my highest point. Suddenly, exactly a year before IIT
Advance 2015, the metaphorical glass was half full and no longer half empty.
There was a calm feeling of conviction of a good possibility of me making it
all the way for a 3 digit rank in IIT. Yes, my math was still well behind
physics and chem but I had a year to work on it, right?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well not exactly. It just so happened that 12th grade started in full flow at
this point and the constant neglect I had given to the school syllabus in 11th
grade was no longer feasible. I couldn't continue just scraping by the school
exams with minimal preparation as I had done in 11th. It dawned on me that I
would have to manage both school and FIITJEE a lot more efficiently if I had
to have a chance with making it to a good college. While physics was chugging
along well, math severely needed a shot in the arm and chem got a whole lot
uglier with 4 (or was it 5?) full organic chapters hastily finished off in
FIITJEE just days before phase test 4. The neglect with the other two subjects
was all too visible with me scoring 20 marks more in physics than chem and
math combined (no I'm not a savant in physics, just an idiot with math :P). In
the middle of all this, a few competitive programming experiences realigned my
goals with respect to computer science and I started liking it almost as much
as I used to obsess with aerospace engineering in the past.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="screwup0"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
For me, this turned into the beginning of a massive decline. For whatever
reason, I succeeded in trashing both the KVPY and the NSEP - my biggest
targets for 12th grade. School marks were about okay, but still less than
ideal. Not in a great shape right now, huh? It proceeded to get worse when on
one day in December 2014 I heard the news that because of my US citizenship, I
was essentially out of the race for NITs, IIITs (note I was still in the
running for IITs though) and a bunch of local colleges in Karnataka as well.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Godammit.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My passion for physics notwithstanding I might as well not have studied at all
for IIT till then. It was a pretty big blow. Fortunately, what the government
taketh, they giveth. I could make it to NITs through their international
program (DASA) solely through subject SAT scores which shouldn't be to big of
a deal given all the study towards JEE. If you've been reading this closely,
you would have probably guessed that even that wasn't exactly straightforward
since the only available day to attempt the subject SAT before the deadline
was December 6, exactly a week after I heard about this scheme. The subject
SATs themselves were uneventful - 2400. Incidentally, at this time math
finally seemed to be shaping up for the first time since I chanced upon this
business with FIITJEE. I could reasonably solve problems when in the mood
which was a big change from how I used to dawdle with the subject earlier.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little did I know that is was the beginning of the biggest low I experienced -
school pre-boards in January 2015 was an unmitigated disaster. 55% in math and
about the same in chem with similarly bad marks across the board in CSc,
physics, and English made for some very unpleasant conversations with my
parents. Forget about JEE, at that point, even making the 80% in boards for
qualifying cutoff was looking distant. Intertwined in this was the new BITS
Hyderabad international admissions program which also made use of the good
subject SAT score! But the twist was that they needed SAT reasoning scores too - which left me (yet again) with no option to attempt it within a week's time
after the pre-boards to make the deadline. Gave it my all - 2220 overall or
1580/1600 CR+Math. With some assurance of BITS Hyderabad, college entrance
exams totally took a backseat from the beginning of this year, the primary
focus from then on being the board exams.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took a lot of effort to get started - those pre-board marks were not going
to fix themselves and I had to make up almost the full year's syllabus in a
bit more than a month to stand a chance. Eventually, the rote-learning mode
grew on me and the board exams came and went in March without too much drama.
Just the day before my last board exam, BITS Hyderabad sent an offer letter
for taking up CSc at an 80% scholarship! For a few sweet minutes the pressure
of the last two years was off.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="entrancexams"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
If you haven't slept off yet reading through all that, here's where it started
to get interesting. Board exams done and dusted left me free to attempt the
set of entrance exams at will - the main ones being JEE Mains/Advance and the
BITSAT. With BITS Hyderabad CSc, I was of the opinion things could only get
better as I could attempt all the exams with a free mind. This went on to be
reasonably true - starting off with JEE Mains on the second Friday of April 2015 - I picked up 206/360 in JEE Mains with a solid 88/120 in physics, 83/120
in chem, and 35/120 (:P) in math. Though I would've hoped for it bit more, it
turned out to be a better score than I thought it would be as the cutoffs had
dropped by 10 marks from the previous year and that very few in my batch had
scored higher. Much later on, it transpired that this JEE Mains score with my
95+% in CBSE would give me a decent shot at getting CSc at NIT, Surathkal
campus, Aerospace Engineering at IISt, and hell, even decent choices (more so with the NTSE) at IIIT-H
had it not been for my US citizenship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this Mains result in hand, it led
me to a crucial decision - study for the BITSAT and go for it all to get CSc
at Pilani campus? Study for JEE Advance instead to salvage a decent rank
especially since BITS unifies their curriculum across campuses? I decided to
go for the BITSAT - after all my math was in no condition for the brunt of JEE
Advance but I had a good shot of making up to a respectable level for the
BITSAT, which is an objectively much easier exam.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="bitsat"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
This quickly turned into an obsession - with a BITSAT textbook by my side I
started optimising and gaming the whole test to the minute with well divided
time sections for all the subjects and strategies for almost all the possible
outcomes at each stage. Math felt like it was finally on par with the other
two subjects. With strong 350-370 scores after attempting all the questions in
all the mock tests without the bonus 12 questions, it looked like that the
dream of two years was finally within my grasp.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, for some inexplicable reason, I felt tremendous pressure just hours
before the exam when I should have been getting a sound sleep. It was awful
and I only managed to catch a few hours of sleep after finally going to sleep
at 2am on the day of the exam scheduled at 830am.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sleep deprivation didn't augur well but that only partially sealed my
fate. The invigilator gave me more rough paper than I was supposed to be given
before the exam (the two rough booklets were somehow glued back to back), only
to realize his mistake when I started the math section.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This can't be happening&lt;/em&gt;, I thought. &lt;em&gt;This isn't how it's supposed to all
end.&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My extra rough sheets were confiscated by the proctor and then it hit me that
this really was the final nail in the coffin. At that very moment the blood
drained from my face realising that my chances were slipping by the second.
With 90 minutes left to go but with no rough paper I was very much on the
verge of giving up knowing that it really couldn't be worse. Math was never my
strongest subject but attempting it without any rough paper was completely out
of the question. Despite all this, I realized that I couldn't just let a dream
of 2 years fall apart for such a pathetic issue and still went on with the
test - guessing everything I could on the math section.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went for the extra 12 questions which were fine but I knew that the damage
done from fluking most of math was irreparable. With the most anxiety I've
ever experienced, I clicked the "Submit Test" button to see how I had done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your score: 307*&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*&lt;em&gt;It was later revised to 311; 118/43&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WTF&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surely it was just my sleep deprived brain that was seeing things, right? I
rubbed my eyes, half expecting the last two digits of the score to reverse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I opened my eyes again. No change. Then I glanced towards the bottom of the
screen and then I knew I had truly screwed the pooch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Correct: 117&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Incorrect: 44&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Correctly marked answers are worth 3 marks and incorrectly marked answers
lose 1 mark from the total)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stumbled out of the exam room/computer lab feeling absolutely numb. Speech
was difficult without a torrent of tears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BITS Pilani CSc, heck, CSc at any BITS campus through BITSAT was an
impossibility. It felt crushing and terrible to work so hard and to get so
close only to ruin everything on the day of the exam for some issue that I had
no control over. That day was not the first time I cried myself to sleep in
those two years, but at least in those times there was a silver lining in getting another
chance to do well in some other exam. There was no other exam left to do well in this time.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strangely the only solace at the time was that I had to give JEE Advance (is
it spelled Advanced? My bad if it's wrong) with absolutely no preparation due
to preparing for the BITSAT instead. So, I ended up with only three days to
prepare for JEE Advance and did nothing more than three previous year's papers
to make sure I wasn't wasting time on any particular section and to ensure I
hadn't lost too much touch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;24 May 2015 was the day. I knew I was going to be in serious trouble before
even opening the question paper - the cover page of the question paper itself
indicated that the next three hours were going to be pure torture with a
ridiculous +4/-2 marking scheme on multiple correct option questions (this
means more than one of the given MCQ options could be correct and failing to
mark all the correct options would make one lose 2 marks), +4/0 integer type
(think: a free response question with values from 0-9), and +2/-1 match the
following (which is a whole lot more sinister than it sounds when you realise
that MORE than one option in a column can be mapped to the other and all the
correct options are required to be marked). It was a blur - all I remember was
being completely deflated and slightly relieved that my ordeal only had
another three hours with Paper 2 which followed a very similarly brutal
marking scheme. I felt like I was in with a chance after doing the 2014 and
2012 question papers but there was no way I could squeeze out a good score
with this. It was a bittersweet feeling after the those long 6 hours - sweet
to think that the sweat and toil of the last two years was finally over and
bitter to see how everything concerning my given entrance exams had fallen
apart in the last week. The first thing I did on getting home from the exam
was to sit down in the garden, on the grass and slowly piece together what
exactly had happened. There were no tears as there had been for making a mess
of the BITSAT - just a quiet resignation and mild shock that dreams had been
shattered for good.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, I'm stuck at the difficult decision with taking BITS Hyderabad CSc
BE or trying for a dual degree program at BITS Goa, taking physics and
eventually CSc.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wow, that's easily been the longest single piece of writing I've ever done. I
typed most of it on my phone on the plane, so apologies if it doesn't make too
much sense. If you've made it all the way here, thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="JEE"></category><category term="Life"></category></entry><entry><title>Nil Sine Pokemon</title><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/pokemon-yes-pokemon.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-04-30T17:05:00+05:30</published><updated>2012-04-30T17:05:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Arnav Dhamija</name></author><id>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2012-04-30:/blog/pokemon-yes-pokemon.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I confess that I haven't been able to tend to this blog as much as I would've
liked. It's not about time (or the lack of it), it's just laziness. Well, a
lot of stuff has happened this month (and a lot of pics have been taken),
which I simply …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I confess that I haven't been able to tend to this blog as much as I would've
liked. It's not about time (or the lack of it), it's just laziness. Well, a
lot of stuff has happened this month (and a lot of pics have been taken),
which I simply can't do justice to by putting it in words.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suppose, I've found a new love as well, some people are going to hate
this...  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/Pokemon-PNG-Pic.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...well actually it's not a new love, this dates back to 2004, so I'll
narrate my history with this incredible video-game.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2004 when I was only 6 years-old, I was everything one could describe
as a Pokemon fan. I used to watch the anime a lot, watched all the released
movies, and even had Pokemon drawing and colouring books. In 2005, I was
introduced to the world of Pokemon video-games, which I never knew existed. I
remember how popular Pokemon used to be in my apartment complex, it was as if
a GameBoy Advance and a Pokemon cartridge was like a piece of clothing, which
you could not &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; have when going outside. The rage was infectious, and I
soon caught on. I got my first Pokemon game as a birthday gift - Pokemon
Sapphire.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, with great exuberance, I got my first Gym badge, saved my game and went to
bed. The next day when I woke up, and loaded the game, I was greeted with this
message:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/deleted-file.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Serious disappointment. I tried saving again, but got the same message. I
thought my Pokemaster career had come to a standstill, which it actually had.
So, for the next few months, all I could do was gaze in envy at my friends'
games which actually saved. Why only for a few months? Because, in February
2006, I got an original FireRed. With the same anxiousness, I tried saving,
and obviously (but to my surprise), it actually worked! Joy. What followed was
me getting an original Emerald as well, so I knew my career was well on its
way. It was a lot of fun, when we were allowed to bring our GameBoys to
school, and see whose Level 100 Mewtwo was better. I must clocked at least a
total of 600 hours on both games, but in the middle of 2007, I was hit by a
GameBoy ban, which didn't end till summer 2008. By then, I totally lost
interest, and the GameBoy took its place as being a convenient paperweight and
dust collector. Never touched it again for three years.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, in 2011, some of my friends came over with their GameBoys to ask me some
Pokemon questions and how to get to Navel Rock without a GameShark. Of course,
I had lost most of my expertise on the subject, and we never got to Navel
Rock. But then, it brought back to me the fond memories of playing Pokemon,
and thinking "Hey, this is fun!". The very next day, I downloaded an emulator
and Emerald ROM, just to relive those moments.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was brilliant, playing Pokemon on that queer low-resolution and basic
pseudo-2.5D models. I couldn't care less about the life-like graphics in other
games. This was for me. I frantically hunted for my FireRed and Emerald
cartridges, but both of them were lost. Lost forever. It was a heart-breaking
moment.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after, I began trawling sites like Bulbapedia and Serebii, to catch up on
what I missed.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was an awful lot. But, looking closer, I saw a very sharp competitive edge
to the game. I was amazed, and soon after, I swallowed the concept of EVs,
IVs, and natures.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I downloaded Pokemon Platinum and DS emulator for fun. I never thought I would
actually play it. I couldn't have been more wrong. I played the whole game and
beat the Battle Frontier with all my newly-gained knowledge.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But soon, I realised, there's no way of playing with a real person like this.
So, I (nervously) asked my parents for a DS + Pokemon Black (I would've never
asked, if I hadn't got scholarship). But that was easily the best things I
could ever buy. A Cosmo Black 3DS and Pokemon Black. All I could've ever
wanted. I've played around 70 Wi-Fi battles, and won like 30 of them. I turned
to sites like &lt;a href="http://smogon.com/"&gt;Smogon&lt;/a&gt;. It was incredible, a whole
community of smart, competitive Pokemon players. It was just the place for me.
A few months ago, I became a member, and my Pokemon journey continues to
advance.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's my story. Hope you guys liked it. No Poke-Haters please!  &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Pokemon"></category><category term="Life"></category><category term="Misc"></category></entry></feed>