<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>A Singularity</title><link>http://arnavdhamija.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/feeds/tag_misc.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2017 10:29:00 +0530</lastBuildDate><item><title>Be "The Opposite"</title><link>http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/be-the-opposite.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;"The Opposite" (S05E21) was a watershed episode for Seinfeld. Not only did the series' direction change hands from Tom Cherones to Andy Ackerman after it, but the plots also became more focussed on the personality flaws in the characters rather than the bizarre situations they got themselves into. "The Opposite" was probably the only episode in which these two tropes combined, making something quite unlike any other Seinfeld episode. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that's not what I'm going to write about in this blog post. "The Opposite" has personal meaning for other reasons. As a short summary of the A-plot of this episode - George, a stout, balding, middle-aged man with no prospects with either a career or the opposite sex decides to act contrary to every instinct he's ever had. In a span of less than a day he ends up with a new partner, a job with the New York Yankees, and moves out from his parents' house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though contrived for comical purposes, this episode holds something very profound under its veil of light-hearted comedy. The series goes to show that even when it's painfully obvious that you're clearly doing something wrong, it can be impossible to get out of the self-induced loop of listening to your instincts. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jerry also drives this home with an understatedly profound remark in this episode, &lt;em&gt;"If every instinct you have is wrong...then the opposite would have to be right!"&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="youtube youtube-16x9"&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/cKUvKE3bQlY" allowfullscreen seamless frameBorder="0"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it's a primal urge to follow your instincts, after all, your instincts are a product of your past experiences which have kept you alive till now. On the other hand, I feel a lot of it also has to do with getting into the comfort zone of being able to challenge your own perceptions. When you've been doing something wrong unconsciously, it becomes much harder to accept the fact that you were doing it wrong later on. Your brain accustoms itself to behaving in a certain way to a stimulus and left unchecked, this becomes a part of your personality. This is why I think shifting out of self-harmful behavior is so hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been a victim of falling to the trap of my own instincts ever since I joined college. Through much time spent brooding and many moments of soul-searching through my daily diary entries, I was exactly aware of what I was unhappy with in life and what I had to do to fix it. Most of my problems could be traced down to a lack of self-esteem, but I was more than willing to wallow in pity than do anything about it. It was only a few months ago I decided to improve things by increasing physical activity and social exposure. There were many times I had a familiar nagging of doubt, but this too subsided as soon as I saw things &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; actually get better by not listening to yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a poignant quote I've saved from Anne Lammot's Bird by Bird about not listening to the radio station in your head - the radio station KFKD, or K-Fucked:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"If you are not careful, station KFKD will play in your head twenty-four hours a day, nonstop, in stereo. Out of the right speaker in your inner ear will come the endless stream of self-aggrandizement, the recitation of one’s specialness, of how much more open and gifted and brilliant and knowing and misunderstood and humble one is. Out of the left speaker will be the rap songs of self-loathing, the lists of all the things one doesn’t do well, of all the mistakes one has made today and over an entire lifetime, the doubt, the assertion that everything that one touches turns to shit, that one doesn’t do relationships well, that one is in every way a fraud, incapable of selfless love, that one has no talent or insight, and on and on and on. You might as well have heavy-metal music piped in through headphones while you’re trying to get your work done."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe the best way out lies in our mistakes, or rather the opposite of them.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Arnav Dhamija</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2017 10:29:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2017-12-28:blog/be-the-opposite.html</guid><category>Life</category><category>Misc</category></item><item><title>ThinkPad 13: Thoughts after 18+ months</title><link>http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/thinkpad-13-review.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It's been over a year since I switched laptops and I want to share my thoughts on my current one - the &lt;a href="https://www3.lenovo.com/us/en/laptops/thinkpad/thinkpad-13-series/ThinkPad-13-Windows-2nd-Gen/p/22TP2TX133E"&gt;Lenovo ThinkPad 13&lt;/a&gt; Gen 1. Before getting this laptop, I had been using a Lenovo IdeaPad G580 which I had gotten back in 2013. While that laptop suited my needs at the time, the unwieldy 15.6" display, sub-standard 2 hrs battery life, and weight of 2.8kg just wasn't cutting it for college. I decided to go for a smaller laptop with good battery life to replace it. I was pretty satisfied with the performance of the IdeaPad so anything as good or better than its i5-3230M was enough for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first laptop which I looked at was the Asus UX305UA which ticked most of my boxes. However, some reviews had stated that its build quality was questionable so I decided to hold out for a better laptop. I later stumbled upon the Lenovo ThinkPad T460(s) which looked perfect for my needs but was just a touch out of my budget. While I was considering this, news began to surface about a 13.3" ThinkPad releasing soon, later to be known as the ThinkPad 13.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn't an easy decision between the T460s and the 13. The T460s was definitely a more charming laptop but there were just too many drawbacks for it to be a serious contender. I found several negative reviews regarding the battery life and the 1080p display lottery. The ThinkPad 13 wasn't without issues of its own, but there wasn't a single review that hadn't sung praises about its keyboard, battery life, and overall value proposition. Plus it came with a USB Type-C port, dual upgradeable RAM slots, and was at least $200 cheaper than a comparatively specced T460s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got the silver version of the ThinkPad 13. Die-hard ThinkPad fans may condemn a non-black ThinkPad, but I think it looks great. Plus, the silver version came with the free 1080p IPS display upgrade. It also has a better choice of materials with an aluminium lid in place of the ABS plastic lid found on the black version of the ThinkPad 13.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I configured my laptop with the following specs for $720 (₹46500):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intel Core i5-6300U Processor (3MB Cache, up to 3.00GHz)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Windows 10 Home 64 English&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8GB DDR4-2133 SODIMM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intel HD Graphics 520&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;KYB SR ENG&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3cell 42Wh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UltraNav (TrackPoint and ClickPad) without Fingerprint Reader&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Software TPM Enabled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;720p HD Camera&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;256 GB Solid State Drive, SATA3 OPAL2.0 - Capable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;45W AC Adapter - US(2pin)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intel Dual Band Wireless-AC(2x2) 8260, Bluetooth Version 4.1 vPro&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;13.3" FHD (1920 x 1080) IPS Anti-Glare, 220 nits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't think the Windows 10 version is available in India presently. I believe a watered down Chromebook version is available on Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I was saving a fair bit of money by not buying the T460s, I maxed out the CPU with the i5-6300U though I don't ever see myself using vPro. The other upgrades were the RAM and SSD to 8GB and 256GB respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ThinkPad 13 Gen 2 and Gen 1 share the same chassis, so most of the parts of this review regarding build quality, I/O, and keyboard apply for the Gen 2 as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Build Quality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pretty&lt;/em&gt; decent. At 1.4kg it's not the smallest or lightest 13.3" laptop available, but it's small enough to not matter. Given the number of I/O ports onboard, it's a very acceptable compromise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can immediately tell it isn't made from the fancy composites of the X1 Carbon or the magnesium alloy of the T/X/P series ThinkPads. Yet the plastic frame of the laptop is good quality and can easily stand out on its own. Compared to other ThinkPads I've tried, it feels considerably better built than the E470 and the X1 Yoga and is on par, if not better than the T440p. The P50 is more solid, though it must be kept in mind that the P50 is a much thicker laptop than the 13. The 13's build quality is on another level compared to the Lenovo IdeaPad G580 I had been using before this. Even after a year of heavy use, creaking on twisting the frame is non-existent and nothing feels like it's on the verge of falling apart like it did with the IdeaPad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hinges are nice and tight and the lid gives a satisfying thump on closing. Speaking of which, the aluminium lid is solid and protects the display nicely. However, it does give the laptop a heterogeneous look and feel with the rest of the frame being made of plastic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One aside here, the 13 does have unique touches not found on higher end models. For example, the "i's" in the ThinkPad logo in both the lid and the palm-rest glow and the ThinkPad logo has a really nice brushed finish to it on the lid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opening the laptop for servicing and upgrading is not a good experience. The bottom base is held by 10 captive screws and is incredibly fiddly to pry open. I ended up scratching off some of the paint of the bottom cover in the two times I tried opening the base. That said, upgradability is much better than what you can find on comparable ultrabooks. Both DDR4 RAM slots, the M.2 SATA SSD (no NVMe on the Gen 1 unfortunately), the Wi-Fi card, and battery can be easily replaced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The touchpad has its share of mechanical issues too. It is a clickpad design, similar to that found on MacBooks. Sometimes dust and debris would find its way in the gap between the base of the laptop and the touchpad causing the right button to physically stop clicking. It's a simple problem to fix and all it needs is a swab with a piece of thick paper under the touchpad. Nevertheless, I expected a more robust design. At least this problem isn't exclusive to the 13 as it seems to happen to the T450s as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the plastic construction does have some drawbacks when it comes to scratches. A small section of the lid joining it to the hinges is plastic and is much more scratched up than the aluminium part of it. After a year, the base unit also had some paint rubbing off from the edges. I would suggest buying a carrying sleeve to avoid this from happening. The silver palmrests also have taken a slightly darker shade to the rest of the laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, all the damage is only cosmetic and the laptop has held up pretty well after being jostled around campus for more than a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;I/O&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connectivity is a strong point for the ThinkPad 13. It's impressive to see how many ports there are on a laptop of this size! You get 3 USB-A ports running at USB 3.0 speeds, a full size HDMI port, an SD card reader in which the card goes all the way in, a headphone jack, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; a USB-C port supporting charging and 2160p/60fps video out. There's also Lenovo's proprietary OneLink+ docking solution though I haven't tried this out yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the subject of the USB-C port, a minor nitpick is that it's USB 3.1 Gen1 and doesn't support Thunderbolt. I still much prefer it to the option of having a full size Ethernet port as on the T460s. The USB-C port is so much more flexible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also discovered that all the USB ports support fast (faster?) charging. My phone charges as fast from the laptop's USB port as it does from a 5V/1.5A charger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wireless connectivity is serviced by the Intel 8260 Wi-Fi card, the same one used on all the top-spec 2016 ThinkPads. Speed and connection quality is good and it supports 802.11ac.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Display&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can't really go wrong with a 1080p IPS display on  a 13.3" laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The LG 1080p IPS display on ThinkPad 13 comes with a matte coating. Even for an IPS display, the viewing angles are excellent. 13.3" and 1080p is a sweet spot for sharpness and UIs scale fine in both KDE Neon and Windows 10. Thanks to the matte coating, the screen brightness is perfectly sufficient 90% of the time when I use it. I've hardly run into any instances where I felt the need to crank the screen brightness any higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colour space coverage is reportedly below average for an IPS screen and it really shows when put side by side with a MacBook Pro or a Dell Inspiron 7460. That said, for coding and web-browsing, it's hard to ask for more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Battery Life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ThinkPad 13 is powered by a 42 Wh battery. It has degraded slightly from when I got the laptop - initially the battery was able to hold 46 Wh of charge but now it usually holds 40-41.5 Wh when full. I usually run several Firefox tabs open with some IDE's like VS Code, Atom, or Android Studio on KDE Neon. The laptop is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; energy efficient and power draw rarely climbs above 6.5W at 30% brightness after enabling TLP. My old laptop used to &lt;strong&gt;idle&lt;/strong&gt; at 17W and when people claim that Intel has gimped their CPUs since the IvyBridge era, I think they're disregarding the huge leaps in power efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In more than a year of owning it, I haven't once drained the battery. I've even gotten through 9-5 days at a summer internship solely off battery power. I typically get around 6-8 hours of battery life depending on the usage. I can't speak of how good or bad battery life is on Windows 10 as I've never used it for anything other than gaming, which brings me to my next section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Performance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subjectively, it's quite snappy. A lot of the performance improvements compared to the laptop I owned before this can be chalked up to the SSD. The one used in the ThinkPad 13 I got was the LiteOn L8H-256V2G and it gives about 540MB/sec in sequential reads and 300MB/sec in sequential writes. It's common knowledge how much faster SSDs are than HDDs, but I hadn't expected it the difference in swapping performance to be as enormous as it is. I can hardly tell when Linux starts filling up the swap space on the SSD as the degradation in performance is minimal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The i5-6300U is sufficient for my needs and thermals in the ThinkPad 13 are good enough that the laptop doesn't need to throttle even under prolonged loads. The processor cools passively most of the time and the fan only kicks in under load. Even so, I'm hard pressed to hear the fan below 4000RPM. The CPU is able to overclock to 2.9 GHz on both cores but I've rarely seen it climb over 2.8 GHz. I'm not sure if this is due to the 15W TDP of the SoC or the laptop's conservative policy when it comes to cooling as core temperatures never climb over 75C on Prime95.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as programming goes, it's not struggled with anything I've thrown at it - from building large C++ codebases to running instances of IntelliJ and Android Studio (with the x86 Android emulator) together. The CPU is definitely faster than the i5-3230M in my old laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus, for the first time, gaming isn't a terrible experience on integrated graphics if your expectations are low enough. I can get 30fps in Skyrim Special Edition at 720p and Medium graphics presets with 2X AA. DiRT3 and Mirror's Edge gave about 60fps at 720p with low settings. Sonic Mania works perfectly at 1080p 60fps. On the other hand, it struggled with returning a framerate greater than 30fps on Sonic Generations. Bear in mind that all this is with single channel 8GB RAM. Performance &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be better with dual channel RAM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Load times in all games are much lesser than they would be on a gaming console such as the PS4 thanks to the SSD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, as long as you don't mind running old games at 720p with some sacrifice in visual quality, the integrated Intel HD 520 should be adequate. At least it's good at smooth 4K video playback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Keyboard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Really good! For years, I used to think that the AccuType keyboard on my Lenovo G580 was unbeatable, but that changed as soon as I laid my hands on the ThinkPad 13's keyboard. The keys are perfectly spaced, have amazingly deep travel, and have great texture. I really like the layout too - PgUp/PgDn + Ctrl makes it very easy to switch tabs and Fn and the left Ctrl can be swapped in the BIOS. I don't miss the lack of keyboard backlighting but I would really appreciate something like a ThinkLight found in older ThinkPad's.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that the keyboard on the 13 is &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; the same as the one on the T460s. I learned this by ruining the stock keyboard when doing my weekly round of sterilising all my electronic devices. AliExpress didn't have the silver 13 keyboard but the 13's FRU manual showed that the T460s keyboard (albeit black instead of silver) could be directly dropped in. After a month of waiting to get it shipped from China, it was a simple 10 minute job to replace the keyboard. Props to Lenovo for reusing FRUs and keeping the 13 so serviceable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm pretty happy with the touchpad as well. It has a smooth surface and has a very satisfying physical click to it. Gestures work well and it's supported out of the box on Linux. The TrackPoint and click buttons have become indispensable for programming. However, I'm disappointed about how fast the TrackPoint's coating wears off as it becomes really difficult to use the shallow TrackPoint once this happens. ThinkPads really should ship with some replacement caps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Linux Support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been using an Ubuntu derivative distro on my laptop ever since I got it. In the first few months, I used Kubuntu 16.04 and then later on I switched to KDE Neon (which, incidentally, is based on Ubuntu 16.04). Linux support is remarkable and everything "just works" right out of the box. Older versions of the 4.x Linux kernel had some issues with the touchpad "desyncing" every 15 minutes, but this has by and large been fixed over the last few months. Thanks to the excellent Mesa drivers, 3D performance of the Intel HD 520 is very stable and actually works better than my friend's NVidia Quadro GPU did with Nouveau drivers (not in terms of frame rate, but stability). The Trackpoint works well and all the function keys work perfectly. Also, as mentioned earlier, battery life under Linux is great. I'm curious to see if the OneLink+ works and if the USB-C can output video on Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, there's nothing you're missing by running Linux on the 13 instead of Windows when it comes to hardware support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ThinkPad 13 is a nice laptop, but it's not for everyone. It fits my workflow perfectly with the good keyboard, display, and build quality. However, not everyone needs as many I/O ports as the 13 has and they would probably be better served by the numerous ultrabooks with better displays and bigger batteries. On the other hand, some might jump for a higher-end ThinkPad model like the T460s/T470s with better build quality and connectivity options. That said, the ThinkPad 13 does a lot of things right and fills a niche in the market for small laptops with good keyboards and several ports. A lot of compromises made in the ThinkPad 13 are reasonable and if you can live with these compromises, it definitely is worthy of consideration for your next laptop.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Arnav Dhamija</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 10 Dec 2017 10:29:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2017-12-10:blog/thinkpad-13-review.html</guid><category>Tech</category><category>Misc</category></item><item><title>The Y2038 Glitch</title><link>http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/y2038.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I had written this article a bit more than a year ago for a college magazine. This topic has been done to death in a Q/A format, so if you're looking for something new about Y2038, you probably won't find it here&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time has always been a finicky thing to deal with. Our perception of time without any stimulus is limited to less than an hour. We would be severely crippled without our abundance of electronic devices synchronized by internet atomic clocks. Unfortunately, these electronic devices on which we're so reliant on are heading towards a time based computer disaster on the same scale as the Y2K bug of this millennium - known as the Y2038 problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do computers measure time and what is the Y2038 bug?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All UNIX derivative systems (including your iPhone or Android smartphone) measure time by counting the number of milliseconds that have elapsed from the 00:00 UTC, 1 January 1970. This day and time is known as the UNIX epoch. While this method of measuring time has served us well for a number of years, it faces a severe limitation - the &lt;code&gt;time_t&lt;/code&gt; int variable (an int variable is a part of a program used to hold integral values) in UNIX used to store the number of milliseconds from the epoch is only a 32-bit data type on older 32-bit computers. This means the &lt;code&gt;time_t&lt;/code&gt; variable can only store up to 2&lt;sup&gt;31&lt;/sup&gt; - 1 milliseconds before the counter overflows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: 32-bit systems can hold a 64-bit int by splitting it into two words each of length 32-bits. However, the default int size on 32-bit systems is only 32-bits and a 64-bit int has to be coded separately.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So how long is it between before this overflow?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exactly 2&lt;sup&gt;31&lt;/sup&gt; - 1 milliseconds after 00:00 UTC, 1 January 1970, which is 03:14:07 UTC, 19 January 2038.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So what will happen?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overflow in the integer value will cause &lt;code&gt;time_t&lt;/code&gt; to reset to - (2&lt;sup&gt;31&lt;/sup&gt;) milliseconds. This date is 20:45 UTC, December 1901. This is actually a much more serious situation than just your computer showing a funny date. This has disastrous consequences for systems with 32-bit CPUs as BIOS software, file systems, databases, network security certificates and a wide variety embedded hardware will fail to work. With huge critical machinery such as old electrical power stations controlled by a 32-bit computer, an unmitigated catastrophe is unavoidable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oh no! Does that mean my laptop and smartphone will stop working as well?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depends. The 32-bit &lt;code&gt;time_t&lt;/code&gt; variable has been deprecated and replaced by a 64-bit &lt;code&gt;time_t&lt;/code&gt; variable which will tide us over for the next 2 billion years. 64-bit CPUs are the standard nowadays and most computers running a 64-bit OS on a 64-bit CPU will not face any such consequences from the Y2038 bug as they use the 64-bit length &lt;code&gt;time_t&lt;/code&gt; variable. However, smartphones have only recently shifted to a 64-bit process and 32-bit smartphones and computers will be affected if they are not coded for the 64-bit int length. That is of course, only if you are still using it after 23 years from today :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But how did this even happen? Why couldn't we just use a 64-bit &lt;code&gt;time_t&lt;/code&gt; variable in the first place? It's only 4 bytes bigger!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Short answer: Legacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long answer: The UNIX kernel was created in AT&amp;amp;T and Bell labs in the 1970s. There were many competent programmers working on the project such as Dennis Ritchie of C fame. Initially, Bell engineers used a different method for calculating time, but they found that the counter would only work for 2.5 years. As UNIX was planned to be a long project, they changed the time counter to a 4-byte integer. This of course was also limited to a very finite amount of time. However in the 1970s, the consensus was that computers weren't going to stick around for that much longer and a 60-odd year window was "good enough".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Couldn't they just have just used a 64-byte int anyway?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not really. Computer resources were scarce in the 1970s and 8-bytes of memory to store &lt;code&gt;time_t&lt;/code&gt; was more memory than what engineers were willing to give.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wait a second! Why doesn't &lt;code&gt;time_t&lt;/code&gt; use the unsigned int? Surely UNIX wasn't programmed expecting us to go back in time!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;time_t&lt;/code&gt; variable uses the signed int to account for dates before the UNIX epoch. Dates before 1 January, 1970 are represented in a negative number of milliseconds which is why an overflow would take the computer's date to 1901.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But this is 2017! Can't we just upgrade the &lt;code&gt;time_t&lt;/code&gt; variable to 64-bits?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes we can. In all new software and 64-bit operating systems, the &lt;code&gt;time_t&lt;/code&gt; variable has been changed to 8-bytes. The problem is that all legacy software compiled with other older compilers may be incompatible for recompiling with a newer compiler for an 8-byte int value. The problem doesn't just stop there. Many embedded systems and microcontrollers (including the popular Arduino ATMega based platform) use 16-bit CPUs which simply cannot support an 8-byte integer in a 2-byte word length. Some hardware applications may use proprietary firmware which won't receive updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How can we fix the Y2038 problem?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There isn't any one-solution-fits-all approach for this since it affects several computer architectures, hardware, and software. While it might be easier to just upgrade all old computers with new 64-bit capable ones, there are still many areas where old 32-bit code is still prevalent. Furthermore, the cost of upgrading all the computer hardware is just too exorbitant to be covered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we look at the lessons learned from the past, the Y2K bug was rectified because of the media hype pressuring businesses to update their software to accommodate 4-digit years. Although the Y2038 bug is much more critical and harder to understand than the Y2K bug, there is hope that the same pressure will bring change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for now, only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/2038.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Credits: &lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/"&gt;xkcd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Arnav Dhamija</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2017 15:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2017-06-09:blog/y2038.html</guid><category>Tech</category><category>Misc</category></item><item><title>Blog Migration Complete!</title><link>http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/blog-migration.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Now I finally have my very own domain name! The &lt;a href="http://arnavdhamija.blogspot.in/"&gt;old Blogger site&lt;/a&gt; is still available if anyone wants to see it but for all future intents and purposes, this will be the place where new blog posts will be put up. While I &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; configure all traffic to the Blogger site to redirect to this one, the old site has grown on me so much over the years that I feel that it would be a shame to hide it that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to migrate from Blogger because it is more than evident that Blogger has been getting less love from Google than it deserves. Take for instance, the Blogger web-based post editor - a shining example of an undeveloped relic of Google's products. Posts never autosaved or had any manual version control and a few misplaced keypresses could cause you to lose all your writing progress. Inserting images is a chore and putting up more complicated parts of text such as code blocks and sub-headings is even worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course as with most things in software development, there are workarounds for everything. The work-around which I had used for the last few blog posts was to write directly in Markdown and then convert it to HTML with pandoc to copy paste in the Blogger editor. Even so, this is clearly sub-optimal and I was spending more time wrestling with the Blogger editor to make my pages look good than I was spending writing actual content. The Blogger theme which I was using appealled to me as 13 year old (heck, it still appeals to me), but it was growing long in the tooth and only had basic support for responsive design and mobile devices. With all these things in mind, I started looking for a new home for my blog somewhere in the middle of last December on a break from college.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first looked at &lt;a href="http://wordpress.com/"&gt;WordPress&lt;/a&gt;. At first, it seemed like my search for a new blogging platform would stop here. Open-sourced, a great browser editor, a cohesive Android app, direct editing in Markdown, local installation for testing, and support for plugins made WordPress everything Blogger wasn't. I loved the number of themes and customisation WordPress provided. But the love was short lived, and it ended when I started researching hosting options for WordPress. Most solutions required me to rent a web-server on a monthly basis and I had no idea what tier of server to get as my blog had only recently seen a huge surge in pageviews. Not to mention, the cost of maintaining a website with such a setup was by no means cheap. This is when I started asking to my geeky friends about how they maintained their own personal websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talks were very helpful, it made me realise that a dynamic blogging solution such as WordPress was overkill for a humble blog of less than 30 published posts like this one. Having a static site made so much more sense. I could write directly in Markdown, in the text editor of &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; choice. Not to mention, it made the workflow of writing a blog post just like I wrote code, &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;git commit&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt; straight to GitHub Pages. GitHub Pages, by the way, offers completely &lt;em&gt;free&lt;/em&gt; hosting for static sites. This means that the only thing I would need to pay for would be the custom domain name, a nominal ₹700 ($10) a year, an amount half of what I would be paying for a month of paid hosting. Plus, it would let me get my hands dirty with a bit of web development, something which I had pushed back for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to start this - what I knew was going to be painful task at about 11pm on a night I just knew I wouldn't be able to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step was to convert all my Blogger posts to Markdown. There were some tools online but all of them messed up the conversion pretty badly. After some more digging, I ended up using Aaron Swartz's &lt;a href="https://github.com/aaronsw/html2text"&gt;html2text&lt;/a&gt; Python library which did a better job than other solutions in generating some useful Markdown. I still needed to edit every generated Markdown file by hand to make it something I would be happy with using on my site. I then had to export all the images I had on my Blogger site. This lead to a few more laborious hours of saving each image on the site by hand (Right Click -&amp;gt; View as Image -&amp;gt; Save As). It did cross my mind to automate everything with a script, but it was going to take more time to automate everything and check if the automation was working than it was to do the grunt work of pulling the images. With all the resources safely on my laptop and backed on my Dropbox, I took the next step of looking at static site generators to convert my lovingly handmade Markdown files to HTML.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitHub Pages seemed to heavily advocate &lt;a href="http://jekyllrb.com/"&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; so I went with it first. With some tinkering to get the Ruby dependencies installed and posts adapted for Jekyll with the Front Matter content, I managed to get a pretty presentable blog running on localhost:4000/ at 5am on that day. With a quick push to my &lt;a href="http://shortstheory.github.com/"&gt;github.io&lt;/a&gt; site, I decided to call it a night and slept off a sleep-deprived session of hacking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next few days I played with some more Jekyll themes and found that there were many things I didn't like about it. For one thing, it was written in Ruby which I have no experience with. Themes didn't look easy to work with and there was no native support for tags (there is a workaround for this, but due to my lack of Ruby-fu, it all looked terribly arcane to me). I then put the blog migration on the back burner for a while to work on projects at my college's Automation &amp;amp; Robotics Club.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks later, I took a look at the blog project with some new perspective. I started by poking around for alternatives to Jekyll. There was one such alternative which ticked all my boxes - a static site generator called &lt;a href="https://blog.getpelican.com/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;. As WordPress looked inherently superior to Blogger, Pelican looked inherently superior to Jekyll for what I wanted to do with it. For example, it had built-in support for tags, had a theming engine, supported Markdown &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; reStructuredText, and had several easy to install plugins. Above all, Pelican is written in Python which made it so much easier for me to mess around with it. There were some more modifications to make to the Markdown files (particularly with the post metadata), but it was so trivial that it didn't pain one bit to modify all the files. Not too long after I settled on Pelican, I found a theme which made my blog look exactly how I wanted it to look. The &lt;a href="https://github.com/PurePelicanTheme"&gt;Pure Single&lt;/a&gt; theme also has nifty support for custom sidebar images, which I used on some select &lt;a href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/t2-years-and-counting-iit-jee.html"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/gsoc-report-wrapping-up-gsoc-2016.html"&gt;posts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was some initial trouble with setting a blog subfolder in the site and getting images to work on some auto-generated sites (such as the Tags and Categories pages). It later turned out that it was some problem with localhost/ not finding the paths correctly to the images and the site was totally fine when published to the GitHub Pages site. After only three days of using Pelican, I had something which I was willing to show off. The next step was much more straightforward for a change - registering a domain name. I looked into a few options such as GoDaddy, Hover, and Namecheap. Namecheap had positive reviews (unlike GoDaddy) and was the cheapest of the lot. The site configuration to serve pages from GitHub's servers was not more than a 10 minute procedure, and I finally had the site you are reading this article on right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be a lot more changes coming up on this blog, some of them aesthetic and some functional. I'm also probably going to change the name of this blog sometime soon, to something which is more reflective of my current sensibilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Arnav Dhamija</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2017 23:50:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2017-02-05:blog/blog-migration.html</guid><category>Misc</category><category>Programming</category></item><item><title>Nil Sine Pokemon</title><link>http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/pokemon-yes-pokemon.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I confess that I haven't been able to tend to this blog as much as I would've
liked. It's not about time (or the lack of it), it's just laziness. Well, a
lot of stuff has happened this month (and a lot of pics have been taken),
which I simply can't do justice to by putting it in words.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suppose, I've found a new love as well, some people are going to hate
this...  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/Pokemon-PNG-Pic.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...well actually it's not a new love, this dates back to 2004, so I'll
narrate my history with this incredible video-game.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2004 when I was only 6 years-old, I was everything one could describe
as a Pokemon fan. I used to watch the anime a lot, watched all the released
movies, and even had Pokemon drawing and colouring books. In 2005, I was
introduced to the world of Pokemon video-games, which I never knew existed. I
remember how popular Pokemon used to be in my apartment complex, it was as if
a GameBoy Advance and a Pokemon cartridge was like a piece of clothing, which
you could not &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; have when going outside. The rage was infectious, and I
soon caught on. I got my first Pokemon game as a birthday gift - Pokemon
Sapphire.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, with great exuberance, I got my first Gym badge, saved my game and went to
bed. The next day when I woke up, and loaded the game, I was greeted with this
message:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/deleted-file.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Serious disappointment. I tried saving again, but got the same message. I
thought my Pokemaster career had come to a standstill, which it actually had.
So, for the next few months, all I could do was gaze in envy at my friends'
games which actually saved. Why only for a few months? Because, in February
2006, I got an original FireRed. With the same anxiousness, I tried saving,
and obviously (but to my surprise), it actually worked! Joy. What followed was
me getting an original Emerald as well, so I knew my career was well on its
way. It was a lot of fun, when we were allowed to bring our GameBoys to
school, and see whose Level 100 Mewtwo was better. I must clocked at least a
total of 600 hours on both games, but in the middle of 2007, I was hit by a
GameBoy ban, which didn't end till summer 2008. By then, I totally lost
interest, and the GameBoy took its place as being a convenient paperweight and
dust collector. Never touched it again for three years.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, in 2011, some of my friends came over with their GameBoys to ask me some
Pokemon questions and how to get to Navel Rock without a GameShark. Of course,
I had lost most of my expertise on the subject, and we never got to Navel
Rock. But then, it brought back to me the fond memories of playing Pokemon,
and thinking "Hey, this is fun!". The very next day, I downloaded an emulator
and Emerald ROM, just to relive those moments.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was brilliant, playing Pokemon on that queer low-resolution and basic
pseudo-2.5D models. I couldn't care less about the life-like graphics in other
games. This was for me. I frantically hunted for my FireRed and Emerald
cartridges, but both of them were lost. Lost forever. It was a heart-breaking
moment.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after, I began trawling sites like Bulbapedia and Serebii, to catch up on
what I missed.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was an awful lot. But, looking closer, I saw a very sharp competitive edge
to the game. I was amazed, and soon after, I swallowed the concept of EVs,
IVs, and natures.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I downloaded Pokemon Platinum and DS emulator for fun. I never thought I would
actually play it. I couldn't have been more wrong. I played the whole game and
beat the Battle Frontier with all my newly-gained knowledge.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But soon, I realised, there's no way of playing with a real person like this.
So, I (nervously) asked my parents for a DS + Pokemon Black (I would've never
asked, if I hadn't got scholarship). But that was easily the best things I
could ever buy. A Cosmo Black 3DS and Pokemon Black. All I could've ever
wanted. I've played around 70 Wi-Fi battles, and won like 30 of them. I turned
to sites like &lt;a href="http://smogon.com/"&gt;Smogon&lt;/a&gt;. It was incredible, a whole
community of smart, competitive Pokemon players. It was just the place for me.
A few months ago, I became a member, and my Pokemon journey continues to
advance.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's my story. Hope you guys liked it. No Poke-Haters please!  &lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Arnav Dhamija</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2012 17:05:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2012-04-30:blog/pokemon-yes-pokemon.html</guid><category>Pokemon</category><category>Life</category><category>Misc</category></item><item><title>After the exams...</title><link>http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/after-exams.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Well, today concluded a week's long affair of exertion. To be honest, it
really wasn't a lot of work this time. Can't say that these exams really ended
on a high note with every student's perennial fear - Hindi.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photography's awesome! Expect pictures in my upcoming posts.  &lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Arnav Dhamija</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2011 19:39:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2011-09-20:blog/after-exams.html</guid><category>Misc</category></item><item><title>Before the exams...</title><link>http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/before-exams.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I really haven't been doing justice to this blog for quite some time. It's
probably out of laziness that I couldn't bring myself to update it either.
With the advent of Pokemon Platinum on the emulator, factor the time I want to
spend on this to zero.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That can change now. Queer time to restart, few days prior to the exams.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Arnav Dhamija</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2011 20:45:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2011-09-09:blog/before-exams.html</guid><category>Misc</category></item><item><title>My First Post on My First Blog</title><link>http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/my-first-blog.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Blogging. Well, something I've wanted to do earnestly for some time.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And just as well, this is and will be my very first post.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(May 8. The day of the 2011 National NTSE round. MAT lifted my hopes but SAT
equally crushed them. Time will tell the efforts.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Arnav Dhamija</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2011 10:58:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2011-05-09:blog/my-first-blog.html</guid><category>FirstPost</category><category>Misc</category></item></channel></rss>