<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Weblog - College</title><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/feeds/tag_college.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://arnavdhamija.com/</id><updated>2017-07-20T20:30:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>On College Students</title><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/on-college-students.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-07-20T20:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-07-20T20:30:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Arnav Dhamija</name></author><id>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2017-07-20:/blog/on-college-students.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As a school kid, I was always fascinated by meeting college students from top tier colleges. There was something surreal in the way they talked and they confidently stood with T-shirts proudly proclaiming the name of their alma mater. I used to have the impression that no matter what came …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As a school kid, I was always fascinated by meeting college students from top tier colleges. There was something surreal in the way they talked and they confidently stood with T-shirts proudly proclaiming the name of their alma mater. I used to have the impression that no matter what came in the future, there was a certain justification of their abilities and intelligence. Perhaps society had conditioned me to think as such. Maybe their apparent confidence was a just a projection of how I thought it would feel to be in a top tier college.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It struck me just recently that everyone in my college is of the same surreal breed I used to look upto. But now, the magic is lost on me. It's no longer the case that simply being admitted to a Tier-1 college would give one opportunities otherwise impossible. At the same time, the name of the college on your degree matters little if you haven't done enough legwork in college to justify being called an "Engineer".&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Life"></category><category term="College"></category></entry><entry><title>What I've been upto</title><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/this-semester-has-gone-little-too-fast.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-19T11:09:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-12-19T11:09:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Arnav Dhamija</name></author><id>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2016-12-19:/blog/this-semester-has-gone-little-too-fast.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This semester has gone a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; too fast for my liking. Though there were
plenty of good memories and takeaways from this semester, it has been by far
my most stressful time in this college yet. Between taking on a number of
technical projects and trying to rescue a sharply …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This semester has gone a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; too fast for my liking. Though there were
plenty of good memories and takeaways from this semester, it has been by far
my most stressful time in this college yet. Between taking on a number of
technical projects and trying to rescue a sharply falling SG due to a poor T1,
there has been very little free time this sem. Above all, this sem has shown
me just how limited of a resource brain power is. Thinking about solving
problems wears me out much more easily than it used to.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's not to say what I've been doing is all drudgery. Some interesting
projects that I've been working on:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;GSoC 2016 Project - kio-stash&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yup, this &lt;a href="https://github.com/KDE/kio-stash"&gt;project&lt;/a&gt; has been in the pipeline
for months. While it (mostly) works on a clean install of KDE, it has some
bugs with copying with mtp:/ device slaves and isn't very well integrated with
Dolphin yet. It is in my best interest to have this shipped with KDE
Frameworks as soon as possible, so I'm looking into patching Dolphin with
better, more specific action support for my project.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;IEEE Signal Processing Cup 2017 - Real-Time Beat Tracking Challenge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The premise of this project doesn't seem very complicated - a team just needs
to submit an algorithm which can successfully detect the beats in a song in
real-time on an embedded device. Heck, I had already implemented the same on
an Arduino with a microphone for rather &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lMb1XScNgOs"&gt;fancy lighting in my hostel
room&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately, as I've
learned the hard way, anything that looks simple is deceptive and this project
is a perfect example. For one thing, a song by itself in the amplitude-time
domain is nearly impossible to extract any data from, so it requires a (Fast)
Fourier Transform to extract frequency bin amplitudes to get anything useful
from it. Next, obtaining beat onset and detection requires generating a
tempogram to find the BPM of a song to find the approximate beat positions.
There are many interesting approaches and different algorithms to solve this
problem. Fortunately, I'm not doing this alone and the seniors I'm working
with have a better understanding of the more difficult mathematical components
of this project, leaving me free to code in C++ and deploy it on actual
hardware.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;foss@bphc&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is a society on campus I started with
&lt;a href="https://github.com/aero31aero/"&gt;three&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://github.com/TestSubjector"&gt;programmers&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://github.com/Nischay-
Pro/"&gt;far&lt;/a&gt; more competent than myself. It all started in September this year
when we had the two-day long &lt;a href="https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Hackathon_BPHC"&gt;Wikimedia
Hackathon&lt;/a&gt; on campus.
Though my contribution to Wikimedia was small, I got a lot out of the
hackathon by meeting the people from Amrita University who came for organising
the event. Listening to what
&lt;a href="https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/User:01tonythomas"&gt;Tony&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="http://srijanagarwal.me/"&gt;Srijan&lt;/a&gt; had to say about how much working for
foss@amrita had benefited them made me realise how much room for improvement
there was in BPHC. As far as this society goes, things are still in their
infancy, yet I feel there is just enough critical mass of talent and
enthusiasm in open source development to push this society forward. We even
have our own
&lt;a href="https://fossbphc.github.io/docs/constitution.html"&gt;Constitution&lt;/a&gt;!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Making a personal website?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Blogspot has been a faithful home for this blog for over half a decade,
it is time to move to a modern solution for hosting. Plus setting up a website
will teach me a bit about web development too, and I've needed an excuse to
learn it for a while. Surely it can't be all that hard, right?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Burnout&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the slew of all these technical projects seemed like a good idea at the
time, it has pushed me closer to burning out. It is the same feeling as what I
felt the same time last year, albeit for different reasons.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of it has carried over from studying harder at the end of this sem than I
had done so before. To my surprise, studying under pressure was actually more
effective than it was without. In some ways, it was a throwback to studying
for the number of exams nearly a couple of years ago. It has made me question
whether any of my education was as much for the knowledge as it was for the
desperation of avoiding failure. I still haven't figured it out, but at least
I feel like I'm not as adverse to putting in the hours for getting a decent
CGPA as I had been last semester.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been compromises in other spheres of college life as well,
investing so much time in studying or doing projects has made me cut down my
participation in other clubs and I've quit nearly all the non-technical clubs
I joined last year. There's more than that too - I feel it's much harder to be
fully immersed in anything anymore.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it's just something else which requires more soul searching.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="College"></category><category term="Life"></category><category term="KDE"></category></entry><entry><title>What do I do now?</title><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/what-do-i-do-now.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-04-14T01:38:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-04-14T01:38:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Arnav Dhamija</name></author><id>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2016-04-14:/blog/what-do-i-do-now.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I spend a lot of time thinking since I've joined college.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had postponed a lot of introspection during the two years I spent slogging
away for the JEE. But now, with ample free time and practically no requirement
to go to classes, I've finally got some time to look …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I spend a lot of time thinking since I've joined college.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had postponed a lot of introspection during the two years I spent slogging
away for the JEE. But now, with ample free time and practically no requirement
to go to classes, I've finally got some time to look back and see how things
have turned out. College started off on the back foot, and while 1-1 had its
charms, I wasn't exactly happy about how things had turned out at the time due
to a bad time with the &lt;a href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/t2-years-and-counting-iit-jee.html#entrancexams"&gt;entrance exams&lt;/a&gt; for all the
&lt;a href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/t2-years-and-counting-iit-jee.html#bitsat"&gt;wrong&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/t2-years-and-counting-iit-jee.html#screwup0"&gt;reasons&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I digress, as time has passed, I have learned to live with my failure a
little better every day, though it still sticks out like a sore thumb on an
otherwise decent academic profile. Despite this, it has been an interesting
exercise is to compare what I expected from college a year ago and reality.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, BITS Pilani (this applies to all campuses, but in this case,
Hyderabad Campus) has some of best internal systems among &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; Indian
colleges. Optional attendance, good grading system, decent infrastructure, and
a lot of freedom is more than what can be asked for in a lot of other colleges.
Despite some glaring flaws such as the lack of a solid technical culture, this
college has punched above its weight for a new institution.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as an engineering utopia? I feel like we are way short of the mark &lt;a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/technology/technology/2013/02/aaron_swartz_he_wanted_to_save_the_world_why_couldn_t_he_save_himself.html"&gt;Aaron&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9vz06QO3UkQ&amp;amp;nohtml5=False"&gt;Swartz&lt;/a&gt; mentioned
in his &lt;a href="http://www.aaronsw.com/weblog/visitingmit"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Perhaps it’s natural, when doing something so greedy and practical as a
startup, to pine for the idealized world of academia. Its image as a place in
an idyllic location filled with smart people has always been attractive; even
more so with the sense that by being there one can get smarter simply through
osmosis. People describe a place of continual geekiness, of throwing chemicals
into the river and building robots in free time. A magical place for hackers
to just enjoy themselves."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This aside, I am of the opinion that the version of me a year ago would have
been sorely disappointed by the version of me today. I feel that I was &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt;
more hardworking and efficient back at that time. The two years in JEE
preparation were undoubtedly the worst years of my school life but now looking
back, those dark days brought out the best in me in the briefest of
moments. Had I not prepared for JEE at all, I would have had no idea just how driven and hard-working I could be
for a goal that would always be just a touch out of view.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite my frustrations with life during JEE preparation, the epiphanies I
used to have on weekly basis with studying physics kept me going.
It was a positive feedback loop with no goading required. On the other hand I
can't remember the last time I actually enjoyed learning something in class in
this college. I hope it isn't a sign of things to come when I start
"engineering" coursework in my second year but as of now, I have pretty much lost all
motivation to study.  The unbridled enthusiasm I used to have when studying
for the entrance exams and the giddy thoughts of making batshit crazy projects in
college has dwindled. In my first semester, it was a convenient excuse to
blame this on burnout after pushing my limits for two years but I've come to
realize that the reason is probably shallower than that. It's not just with
academics though - wasting time &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; feels painful but I have nothing I
want to do to fill in the gaps. Is there a cause for this? Probably. Have I
figured it out? Absolutely not.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels like an artificial conflict of time between these misguided academic
pursuits and to actually work on something worthwhile. I could put up with
it in school with the thought that there would be enough free time to pursue
this in college - and while there is - it begs the question why such
artificial restraints on time in the form of exams are always looming in the
first place.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point of time, I don't know what to do. With compre in half a month
but a &lt;a href="https://goo.gl/BYOWdG"&gt;GSoC project&lt;/a&gt; and a couple other projects I've
planned in the pipeline, it's a pretty easy decision to make the choice of
which one of these two things I would want to work on. For a CGPA for which I
cannot care for anymore, it might be one of the worst decisions I can make.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Rants"></category><category term="College"></category><category term="Life"></category></entry></feed>