<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>A Singularity</title><link>http://arnavdhamija.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/feeds/tag_gsoc.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 01:45:00 +0530</lastBuildDate><item><title>GSoC Report - Wrapping up GSoC 2016</title><link>http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/gsoc-report-wrapping-up-gsoc-2016.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;That’s it. After a &lt;a href="https://github.com/KDE/kio-stash/graphs/contributors"&gt;combined total&lt;/a&gt; of 217 git commits, 6,202 lines of code added, and
4,167 lines of code deleted, GSoC 2016 is finally over.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/Screenshot_20160830_014801.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These twelve weeks of programming have been a very enriching experience for me
and making this project has taught me a lot about production quality software
development. Little did I know that a &lt;a href="https://github.com/shortstheory/filetray-very-early-alpha-idea-
thingy"&gt;small
project&lt;/a&gt; I had put together in a 6 hour session of messing around with Qt would
lead to something as big as this!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been many memorable moments throughout my coding period for the
GSoC - such as the first time I got an ioslave to
&lt;a href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/gsoc-update-1-beginning.html"&gt;install&lt;/a&gt; correctly, to writing its “Hello World”
&lt;a href="{filename}/2016-06-21-gsoc-update-writing-kio-slave-101.md"&gt;equivalent&lt;/a&gt;, and getting a basic implementation of the project up and
running by doing a series of dirty hacks with Dolphin’s code. There were also
times when I was so frustrated with debugging for this project, that I wanted
to do nothing but smash my laptop’s progressively failing display panel with
the largest hammer I could find. The great mentorship from my GSoC mentor and
the premise of the GSoC program itself kept me going. This also taught me an
important lesson with regards to software development - no one starting out
gets it right on their first try. It feels like after a long run of not quite
getting the results I wanted, the GSoC is the thing which worked out for me as
everything just fell into place.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a technical digression here, which you can feel free to skip through
if you don’t want to get into the details of the project.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following up from the &lt;a href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/gsoc-update-tinkering-with-kio.html"&gt;previous&lt;/a&gt; blog post, with the core features of the
application complete, I had moved on to unit testing my project. For this
project, unit testing involved writing test cases for each and every component
of the application to find and fix any bugs. Despite the innocuous name, unit
testing this project was a much bigger challenge than I expected. As for one
thing, the ioslave in my project is merely a controller in the MVC system of
the virtual Stash File System, the Dolphin file manager, and the KIO Slave
itself. Besides, most of the ioslave’s functions have a void return type, so
feeding the slave’s functions’ arguments to get an output for checking was not
an option either.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This led me to use an approach, which my mentor aptly called “black box
testing”.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this approach, one writes unit tests testing for a specific action and then
checking for whether the effects of the said action are as expected. In this
case, the ioslave was tested by giving it a test file and then apply some of
the ioslave’s functions such as copy, rename, delete, and stat. From there,
through a bunch of QVERIFY calls is to check whether the ioslave has completed
the operation successfully. Needless to say, this approach is far more
convoluted to write unit tests for as it required checking each and every test
file for its properties in every test case. Fortunately, the
&lt;a href="http://doc.qt.io/qt-4.8/qtestlib-manual.html#qtestlib"&gt;QTestLib&lt;/a&gt; API is
pretty well documented so it wasn’t difficult to get started with writing unit
tests. I also had a template of what a good test suite should look like thanks
to David Faure’s excellent work on implementing automated unit testing for the
Trash ioslave. With these two tools in hand, I started off with writing unit
tests shortly before the second year of college started.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As expected, writing black box unit tests was a PITA in its own right. The
first time I ran my unit test I came up with a dismal score of 6 unit tests
passed out of the 17 I had written. This lead me to go back and check whether
my unit tests were testing correctly at all. It turned out that I had made so
many mistakes with writing the unit tests that an entire rewrite of the test
suite wasn’t unwarranted.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a rewrite of the test cases completed, I ran the test suite again. The
results were a bit better - 13 out of the 17 test cases passed, but 4 failed
test cases - enough reason for the project to be unshippable. Looking into the
issue a bit deeper, I found out that all the D-Bus calls to my ioslave for
copy and move operations were not working correctly! Given that I had spent so
much time on making sure the ioslave was robust enough, this was a mixed
surprise. Finally, after a week of rewriting and to an extent, refactoring the
rename and copy functions of the ioslave, I got the best terminal output I
ever wanted from this project.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/Screenshot_20160829_184812.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Definitely the highest point of the GSoC for me. From there on out, it was a
matter of putting the code on the slow burner for cleaning up any leftover
debug statements and for writing documentation for other obscure sections.
With a net total of nearly 2000 lines of code, it far surpasses any other
project I’ve done in terms of size and quality of code written.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some points in the project, I felt that the stipend was far too generous,
for many people working on KDE &lt;em&gt;voluntarily&lt;/em&gt; produce projects much larger
thann mine. In the end, I feel the best way to repay the generosity is to
continue with open source development - just as the GSoC intended. Prior to
the GSoC, open source was simply an interesting concept to me, but
contributing a couple of thousands of lines of code to an open source codebase
has made me realise just how powerful open source is. There were no
restrictions on when I had to work (usually my productivity was at its peak at
outlandish late night hours), on the machine I used for coding (a trusty
IdeaPad, replaced with a much nicer ThinkPad), or on the place where I felt
most comfortable coding from (a toss up between my much used study table or
the living room). In many ways, working from home was probably the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt;
environment I could ask for when it came to working on this project. Hacking
on an open source project gave me a sense of gratification solving a problem
in competitive programming never could have.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Google Summer of Code may be over, but my journey with open source
development has just begun. Here’s to even bigger and better projects in the
future!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Arnav Dhamija</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 01:45:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2016-08-30:blog/gsoc-report-wrapping-up-gsoc-2016.html</guid><category>GSoC</category><category>KDE</category></item><item><title>GSoC Update: Tinkering with KIO</title><link>http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/gsoc-update-tinkering-with-kio.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I'm a lot closer to finishing the project now. Thanks to some great support
from my GSoC mentor, my project has turned out better than what I had written
about in my proposal! Working together, we've made a lot of changes to the
project.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For starters, we've changed the name of the ioslave from "File Tray" to
"staging" to "stash". I wasn't a big fan of the name change, but I see the
utility in shaving off a couple of characters in the name of what I hope will
be a widely used feature.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the ioslave is now completely independent from Dolphin, or any KIO
application for that matter. This means it works &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; the same way across
the entire suite of KIO apps. Given that at one point we were planning to make
the ioslave fully functional only with Dolphin, this is a major plus point for
the project.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, the backend for storing stashed files and folders has undergone a
complete overhaul. The first iteration of the project stored files and folders
by saving the URLs of stashed items in a QList in a custom "stash" daemon
running on top of kded5. Although this was a neat little solution which worked
well for most intents and purposes, it had some disadvantages. For one, you
couldn't delete and move files around on the ioslave without affecting the
source because they were all linked to their original directories. Moreover,
with the way 'mkdir' works in KIO, this solution would never work without each
application being specially configured to use the ioslave which would entail a
lot of groundwork laying out QDBus calls to the stash daemon. With these
problems looming large, somewhere around the midterm evaluation week, I got a
message from my mentor about ramping up the project using a "StashFileSystem",
a virtual file system in Qt that he had written just for this project.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The virtual file system is a clever way to approach this - as it solved both
of the problems with the previous approach right off the bat - mkdir could be
mapped to virtual directory and now making volatile edits to folders is
possible without touching the source directory. It did have its drawbacks too - as it needed to stage every file in the source directory, it would require a
lot more memory than the previous approach. Plus, it would still be at the
whims of kded5 if a contained process went bad and crashed the daemon.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the benefits in this case far outweighed the potential cons and
I got to implementing it in my ioslave and stash daemon. Using this virtual
file system also meant remapping all the SlaveBase functions to corresponding
calls to the stash daemon which was a complete rewrite of my code. For
instance, my GitHub log for the week of implementing the virtual file system
showed a sombre 449++/419--. This isn't to say it wasn't productive though -
to my surprise the virtual file system actually worked better than I hoped it
would! Memory utilisation is low at a nominal ~300 bytes per stashed file and
the performance in my manual testing has been looking pretty good.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the ioslave and other modules of the application largely completed, the
current phase of the project involves integrating the feature neatly with
Dolphin and for writing a couple of unit tests along the way. I'm looking
forward to a good finish with this project.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the source for it here: &lt;a href="https://github.com/KDE/kio-stash"&gt;https://github.com/KDE/kio-stash&lt;/a&gt; (did I
mention it's now hosted on a &lt;a href="https://quickgit.kde.org/?p=kio-
stash.git"&gt;KDE repo&lt;/a&gt;? ;) )&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Arnav Dhamija</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 21 Jul 2016 15:18:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2016-07-21:blog/gsoc-update-tinkering-with-kio.html</guid><category>GSoC</category><category>KDE</category></item><item><title>GSoC Update 1: The Beginning</title><link>http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/gsoc-update-1-beginning.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I have officially started my &lt;a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/projects/#5979393230897152"&gt;GSoC
project&lt;/a&gt; under
the mentorship of &lt;a href="https://blog.baloneygeek.com/"&gt;Boudhayan Gupta &lt;/a&gt;and &lt;a href="http://blog.pinak.me/"&gt;Pinak
Ahuja&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project idea's implementation has undergone some changes from what I
proposed. While the essence of the project is the same, it will now no longer
be dependent on Baloo and xattr. Instead, it will use a QList to hold a list
of staged files with a plugin to kiod. My next milestone before the mid-term
evaluation is to implement this in a KIO slave which will be compatible with
the whole suite of KDE applications.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the last two weeks, I've been busy with going through hundreds of lines of
source code to understand the concept of a KIO slave. The KIO API is a very
neat feature of KDE - it provides a single, consistent way to access remote
and local filesystems. This is further expanded to KIO slaves which are
programs based on the KIO API which allow for a filesystem to be expressed in
a particular way. For instance, there is a KIO slave for displaying xattr file
&lt;a href="http://vhanda.in/blog/2014/07/tagging-your-files/"&gt;tags&lt;/a&gt; as a directory under
which each file marked to a tag would be displayed. KIO slaves even expand to
network protocols allowing for remote access using slaves such as http:/,
ftp:/, smb:/ (for Windows samba shares), fish:/, sftp:/, nfs:/, and webdav:/.
My project requires virtual folder constructed of URLs stored in a QList - an
ideal fit for KIO slaves.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, hacking on KIO slaves was not exactly straightforward. Prior to my
GSoC selection, I had no idea on how to edit CMakeLists.txt files and it was a
task to learn to make one by hand. Initially, it felt like installing the
dependencies for building KIO slaves would almost certainly lead to me
destroying my KDE installation, and sure enough, I did manage to ruin my
installation. Most annoying. Fortunately, I managed to recover my data and
with a fresh install of Kubuntu 16.04 with all the required KDE packages, I
got back to working on getting the technical equivalent of a Hello World to
work with a KIO slave.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This too, was more than a matter of just copying and pasting lines of code
from the &lt;a href="https://techbase.kde.org/Development/Tutorials/KIO_Sla
ves/Hello_World"&gt;KDE tutorial&lt;/a&gt;. KIO slaves had dropped the use of .protocol files in the KF5
transition, instead opting for JSON files to store the properties of the KIO
slave. Thankfully, I had the assistance of the legendary &lt;a href="https://behindkde.org/david-faure-2"&gt;David
Faure&lt;/a&gt;. Under his guidance, I managed to
port the KIO slave in the tutorial to a KF5 compatible KIO slave and after a
full week of frustration of dealing with dependency hell, I saw the best Hello
World I could ever hope for:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/kioslave.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baby steps. The next step was to make the KIO slave capable of displaying the
contents of a specified QUrl in a file manager. The documentation for
KProtocolManager made it seem like a pretty straightforward task - apparently
that all I needed to do was to add a "listing" entry in my JSON protocol file
and I would have to re-implement the listDir method inherited from SlaveBase
using a call to SlaveBase::listDir(&amp;amp;QUrl). Unbeknownst to me, the SlaveBase
class actually didn't have any code for displaying a directory! The SlaveBase
class was only for reimplementing its member functions in a derived class as I
found out by going through the source code of the core of kio/core. Learning
from my mistake here I switched to using a ForwardingSlaveBase class for my
KIO slave which instantly solved my problems of displaying a directory.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/helloslave.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fistpump&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to my timeline, the next steps in the project are  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finishing off the KIO slave by the end of this month&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making GUI modifications in Dolphin to accommodate the staging area&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thinking of a better name for this feature?
So far, it's been a great experience to get so much support from the KDE
community. Here's to another two and a half months of KDE development!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Arnav Dhamija</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2016 10:37:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2016-05-30:blog/gsoc-update-1-beginning.html</guid><category>GSoC</category><category>Programming</category><category>KDE</category></item><item><title>It has happened - GSoC 2016 Selection!</title><link>http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/it-has-happened.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Wow!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/photo_2016-04-23_12-26-30.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been selected for the Google Summer of Code!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the better part of the summer vacation, I will now be committing myself to
write code for &lt;a href="https://www.kde.org/"&gt;KDE&lt;/a&gt; to implement my project idea of
implementing a &lt;a href="https://goo.gl/BYOWdG"&gt;virtual folder in Dolphin&lt;/a&gt; to make it
easier to select files.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a primer, the &lt;a href="http://g.co/gsoc"&gt;Google Summer of Code &lt;/a&gt;(GSoC) is an annual
event organized by Google for drawing students to work on open source projects
with a nice stipend, goodies, and fame. The GSoC is a term one would hear
pretty frequently when talking about the technical prowess and coding culture
of a college.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, BITS Pilani - Hyderabad Campus had a record number of a total of
&lt;strong&gt;7&lt;/strong&gt; selections! This is more than double of our previous record. This in
some ways, might be the start of the technical culture wave this campus was
looking for so long.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The File Tray idea for the GSoC came at a difficult time, hardly a month after
the entrance exams in 2015. It was at a time I was frustrated with everything
I had done and I didn't have any energy to pursue anything at all having been
completely drained out by the entrance exams prior to it. From there, the
project sat on the list of "Things I Might Do In The Distant Future". The
project idea was known only to a few close friends and my tiny programming
diary.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was only till November 2015 when I stumbled across the GSoC. I began
looking at open source file managers for which I could implement my project
idea. I had been using Linux with various desktop environments for about 4
years at that point, so I had a pretty decent idea of what to look for.
Writing this feature for GNOME's Nautilus was the first thing I looked into as
I had been using Nautilus for a while and I was a big fan of Nautilus's simple
to use interface. But, the problem was that Nautilus was a C/GTK+ project and
I had no desire to move on to using C after having C++ in my comfort zone for
a very long time. Fortunately, Dolphin, one of the best file managers I had
used since my days of using KDE, used C++/Qt, a toolset I am much better with.
I felt my project idea was a natural fit for Dolphin's Split view mode. KDE
also had an excellent record in the GSoC with a very good number of slots and
a high percentage of successful projects. This began my tryst with Open Source
development.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there on, I taught myself &lt;a href="http://www.qt.io/"&gt;Qt&lt;/a&gt; and during a Diwali
vacation on campus, I managed to make a very rough &lt;a href="https://github.com/shortstheory/filetray-very-early-alpha-idea-
thingy"&gt;prototype
application&lt;/a&gt; of my project after coding for 6 hours straight from 11pm to 5am the
next day. Following this, I subscribed to KDE's mailing lists and after
lurking around for a while, I started asking for feedback on my GSoC idea.
With surprisingly positive feedback from numerous KDE developers, I realized
that there might just be a non-zero chance of getting selected.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things quickly began falling into place and I then moved on to the next step
of hunting around for bugs I could fix and new features I could implement for
Dolphin. The bug-fixing was as enjoyable as it was occasionally frustrating.
Reading over 20000 lines of code certainly took its toll when I had no idea
when how different parts of the application meshed together. In the end,
thanks to the guidance of Dolphin maintainer, Emmanuel Pescosta, I managed to
fix a couple of things for Dolphin and moved on to the next step of making a
proposal for my GSoC application.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting off with making a competent proposal was like launching off ground
zero as there were very few people who had successfully completed the GSoC
from our campus and most of these people had graduated well before this time.
I started digging around for proposals accepted by KDE in previous GSoC's.
What I couldn't get from all the proposals was some sound advice from seniors.
In particular, &lt;a href="https://github.com/naveenjafer"&gt;Naveen Jafer bhaiya&lt;/a&gt; (who also
went on to achieve a GSoC project of his own!) helped me with making my
proposal as good as possible. In the end, after painstakingly checking every
word in my proposal for what felt like the fiftieth time I submitted it on 25
March, only to spend an anxious month waiting for the results which came out
at 1230am IST on April 23. While it still hasn't sunk in yet (!), I am sure
that this will make for an awesome summer vacation!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Arnav Dhamija</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2016 12:28:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2016-04-23:blog/it-has-happened.html</guid><category>GSoC</category><category>KDE</category></item><item><title>GSoC 2016 Project Survey, help me make Dolphin a better File Manager!</title><link>http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/gsoc-2016-project-survey-help-me-make.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Hey everyone!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a first year computer science undergraduate from BITS Pilani, Hyderabad
Campus. I am looking forward to working for KDE for the GSoC.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://developers.google.com/open-source/gsoc/resources/downloads/GSoC2016Logo.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My project idea is based on solving a problem all file managers have had for
years - the lack of an easy to use file selection tool. My project aims to
simplify selecting files from multiple directory trees.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am running a survey to gauge community feedback on my idea and to finalize
the user interface and features list.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The link to my idea proposal can be found here: &lt;a href="https://goo.gl/1Nj4SY"&gt;https://goo.gl/1Nj4SY&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the link to my survey can be found here: &lt;a href="https://goo.gl/forms/5JSZXNganX"&gt;https://goo.gl/forms/5JSZXNganX&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TIA for the feedback : )&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Arnav Dhamija</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2016 21:16:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2016-02-15:blog/gsoc-2016-project-survey-help-me-make.html</guid><category>GSoC</category><category>Programming</category><category>KDE</category></item></channel></rss>