<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>A Singularity</title><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/feeds/tag_rants.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://arnavdhamija.com/</id><updated>2016-04-14T01:38:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>What do I do now?</title><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/what-do-i-do-now.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-04-14T01:38:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Arnav Dhamija</name></author><id>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2016-04-14:blog/what-do-i-do-now.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I spend a lot of time thinking since I've joined college.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had postponed a lot of introspection during the two years I spent slogging
away for the JEE. But now, with ample free time and practically no requirement
to go to classes, I've finally got some time to look back and see how things
have turned out. College started off on the back foot, and while 1-1 had its
charms, I wasn't exactly happy about how things had turned out at the time due
to a bad time with the &lt;a href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/t2-years-and-counting-iit-jee.html#entrancexams"&gt;entrance exams&lt;/a&gt; for all the
&lt;a href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/t2-years-and-counting-iit-jee.html#bitsat"&gt;wrong&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/t2-years-and-counting-iit-jee.html#screwup0"&gt;reasons&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I digress, as time has passed, I have learned to live with my failure a
little better every day, though it still sticks out like a sore thumb on an
otherwise decent academic profile. Despite this, it has been an interesting
exercise is to compare what I expected from college a year ago and reality.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, BITS Pilani (this applies to all campuses, but in this case,
Hyderabad Campus) has some of best internal systems among &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; Indian
colleges. Optional attendance, good grading system, decent infrastructure, and
a lot of freedom is more than what can be asked for in a lot of other colleges.
Despite some glaring flaws such as the lack of a solid technical culture, this
college has punched above its weight for a new institution.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as an engineering utopia? I feel like we are way short of the mark &lt;a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/technology/technology/2013/02/aaron_swartz_he_wanted_to_save_the_world_why_couldn_t_he_save_himself.html"&gt;Aaron&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9vz06QO3UkQ&amp;amp;nohtml5=False"&gt;Swartz&lt;/a&gt; mentioned
in his &lt;a href="http://www.aaronsw.com/weblog/visitingmit"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Perhaps it’s natural, when doing something so greedy and practical as a
startup, to pine for the idealized world of academia. Its image as a place in
an idyllic location filled with smart people has always been attractive; even
more so with the sense that by being there one can get smarter simply through
osmosis. People describe a place of continual geekiness, of throwing chemicals
into the river and building robots in free time. A magical place for hackers
to just enjoy themselves."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This aside, I am of the opinion that the version of me a year ago would have
been sorely disappointed by the version of me today. I feel that I was &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt;
more hardworking and efficient back at that time. The two years in JEE
preparation were undoubtedly the worst years of my school life but now looking
back, those dark days brought out the best in me in the briefest of
moments. Had I not prepared for JEE at all, I would have had no idea just how driven and hard-working I could be
for a goal that would always be just a touch out of view.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite my frustrations with life during JEE preparation, the epiphanies I
used to have on weekly basis with studying physics kept me going.
It was a positive feedback loop with no goading required. On the other hand I
can't remember the last time I actually enjoyed learning something in class in
this college. I hope it isn't a sign of things to come when I start
"engineering" coursework in my second year but as of now, I have pretty much lost all
motivation to study.  The unbridled enthusiasm I used to have when studying
for the entrance exams and the giddy thoughts of making batshit crazy projects in
college has dwindled. In my first semester, it was a convenient excuse to
blame this on burnout after pushing my limits for two years but I've come to
realize that the reason is probably shallower than that. It's not just with
academics though - wasting time &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; feels painful but I have nothing I
want to do to fill in the gaps. Is there a cause for this? Probably. Have I
figured it out? Absolutely not.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels like an artificial conflict of time between these misguided academic
pursuits and to actually work on something worthwhile. I could put up with
it in school with the thought that there would be enough free time to pursue
this in college - and while there is - it begs the question why such
artificial restraints on time in the form of exams are always looming in the
first place.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point of time, I don't know what to do. With compre in half a month
but a &lt;a href="https://goo.gl/BYOWdG"&gt;GSoC project&lt;/a&gt; and a couple other projects I've
planned in the pipeline, it's a pretty easy decision to make the choice of
which one of these two things I would want to work on. For a CGPA for which I
cannot care for anymore, it might be one of the worst decisions I can make.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Rants"></category><category term="College"></category><category term="Life"></category></entry><entry><title>Rantings: Indian Education</title><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/rantings-indian-education.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-02-03T15:40:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Arnav Dhamija</name></author><id>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2012-02-03:blog/rantings-indian-education.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Indian education system has been one with many &lt;strike&gt;ups and&lt;/strike&gt;
downs. Viewing from not an expert's position, not from a parent's position,
not from a teacher's position, but from a high school, bored student's
perspective, this post is just a rant about our muddled education system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CCE&lt;/strong&gt;: This was supposed to be the next big thing to do away with exams.
However, the government's magic wand failed to do much on these counts, and
instead of doing away with exams, it succeeded to give us a cornucopia of
projects and assignments, to keep us busy in our already syncopated free time.
It probably could've done a lot more if they had revised their assessment,
but.....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emphasis on exams&lt;/strong&gt;: What the education board has largely taught the
majority of Indian students is that failure in exams is tantamount to failure
in life. It screams to say that exams are the most important thing that could
have happened since the Big Bang, and that failing could just as well result
in the destruction of the universe itself. It would be an understatement to
say that "10th graders in India suicide", because the existence threatening
virus has got to almost all age groups. For the sake of lives, try to change
these stereotypes, CBSE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lack of thinking problems&lt;/strong&gt;: OK, I know what my fellow students are thinking on
these counts in math (no pun intended), but problems like these are reserved
for "higher classes". It's like slowly walking on a long path and then being
forced to run a marathon. Yeah, these problems can't be left out early for the
benefit of the "average student". Sure, it is tough going early, but it will
pay off in the end. The bar of the "average student" needs to be raised a
notch higher on the metaphoric ladder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want more evidence, just look at India's IMO (International
Mathematics Olympiad) rating of 72nd out of 73 countries. An average South
Korea's 3rd grader is astonishingly  just as good as an average Indian 8th
grader at mathematical/mental ability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hindi&lt;/strong&gt;: As if the subject wasn't terrifying enough, some wise guy decided to
give kids 15 chapters of boredom and then ask arbitrary questions in exams.
With themes ranging from dirt, mud and random biographies, the Hindi syllabus
clearly wasn't reviewed by a person brought up in a ubiquitous English
community. If CBSE can reduce the bar so nonchalantly for sciences, why was
this treatment skipped for Hindi?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uniformed board&lt;/strong&gt;: This probably saves a lot of confusion, but it means that it
needs to cater to all types of society for what the board considers
"relevant". Things like forestry and agriculture are hardly needed in urban
areas, but then again, this is according to me, not them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policies&lt;/strong&gt;: Read plural of policy and not law enforcing officers. RTE plans to
give education to everyone, which sounds like a nice idea, but in reality is
far-fetched. With most 3rd graders failing to pass basic English reading tests
(94% to be exact), something seems to be wrong. Even if they somehow do get
everyone educated, not everyone can get a job in this country, leaving lots of
wasted talent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a more positive note, literacy rates have jumped by over 12% since 2001's
census. Great news, but these shortcomings give one some food for thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comment, criticise and praise at your own will.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Rants"></category></entry><entry><title>7 Billion</title><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/7-billion.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-10-31T19:36:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Arnav Dhamija</name></author><id>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2011-10-31:blog/7-billion.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today the world has reached a new milestone, which has compelled me to change
the very name of this blog itself. Yes, we reached the population landmark of
7,000,000,000 or seven billion according to a UN estimate. According to me
population growth is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a good trend and achieving it has some serious
implications. The world is already ridden with poverty, AIDS and a host of
problems with which the majority of the population can not keep up with. Sure,
we have more people and man-force. But that doesn't help the fact that unlike
population, resources do not reproduce by themselves. Providing for seven
billion odd people is more than what the earth can give.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a breakdown of the world's population growth.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is positive information. The world has only added one billion people in
13 years since the last milestone of six billion. More people would probably
mean higher growth rates. It's not happened in this case due to successful
campaigns from the Chinese - 400 million less births. However, even with the
current growth rate, it will not be sustainable to have more people on this
planet in a few decades.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Food for thought. Comment and express your opinions.  &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Rants"></category></entry><entry><title>'The 1 = Everything' equation</title><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/1-everything-equation.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-09-21T13:57:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Arnav Dhamija</name></author><id>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2011-09-21:blog/1-everything-equation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What's your unlucky number?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"13", say some people  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Nooo, 4", say the others.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My unlucky number's 1. Yup.  The closest whole number to zero really sucks for
me. Cricket: Lost by 1 run. Badminton: 20-21 (no deuces). It's pretty much
everywhere. More so from a competitive exam viewpoint: NSO, IMO, IAIS, they've
all gone up in smoke because of 1 mark. But that really doesn't compare to my
worst defeat.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infosys CTY.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was pretty happy with myself till I got to know of the top six. I couldn't
believe it, so I stormed into the co-coordinator's room.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"How much did I get", I asked.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After fumbling a bit, she said I got 18/20. I didn't know how that could
disqualify me because everyone else got 18/20 as well.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I could've chosen you instead of anyone of the other six. But your mistake,
well, I can't pardon that."  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had messed up on the easiest question in that paper: "What's 25% of 25%?". I
decided not to argue. It really hurt that I screwed up on that. Every morning
for a few months I woke up with the same question, "What good am I in anything
else, if I can't even make it to the top six in my school?".  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scars don't fade easily, and this one didn't heal till a month ago.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There you have it: 'The 1 = Everything' equation.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Rants"></category></entry></feed>