<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>A Singularity</title><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/feeds/tag_pokemon.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://arnavdhamija.com/</id><updated>2012-04-30T17:05:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Nil Sine Pokemon</title><link href="http://arnavdhamija.com/blog/pokemon-yes-pokemon.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-04-30T17:05:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Arnav Dhamija</name></author><id>tag:arnavdhamija.com,2012-04-30:blog/pokemon-yes-pokemon.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I confess that I haven't been able to tend to this blog as much as I would've
liked. It's not about time (or the lack of it), it's just laziness. Well, a
lot of stuff has happened this month (and a lot of pics have been taken),
which I simply can't do justice to by putting it in words.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suppose, I've found a new love as well, some people are going to hate
this...  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/Pokemon-PNG-Pic.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...well actually it's not a new love, this dates back to 2004, so I'll
narrate my history with this incredible video-game.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2004 when I was only 6 years-old, I was everything one could describe
as a Pokemon fan. I used to watch the anime a lot, watched all the released
movies, and even had Pokemon drawing and colouring books. In 2005, I was
introduced to the world of Pokemon video-games, which I never knew existed. I
remember how popular Pokemon used to be in my apartment complex, it was as if
a GameBoy Advance and a Pokemon cartridge was like a piece of clothing, which
you could not &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; have when going outside. The rage was infectious, and I
soon caught on. I got my first Pokemon game as a birthday gift - Pokemon
Sapphire.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, with great exuberance, I got my first Gym badge, saved my game and went to
bed. The next day when I woke up, and loaded the game, I was greeted with this
message:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://arnavdhamija.com/images/deleted-file.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Serious disappointment. I tried saving again, but got the same message. I
thought my Pokemaster career had come to a standstill, which it actually had.
So, for the next few months, all I could do was gaze in envy at my friends'
games which actually saved. Why only for a few months? Because, in February
2006, I got an original FireRed. With the same anxiousness, I tried saving,
and obviously (but to my surprise), it actually worked! Joy. What followed was
me getting an original Emerald as well, so I knew my career was well on its
way. It was a lot of fun, when we were allowed to bring our GameBoys to
school, and see whose Level 100 Mewtwo was better. I must clocked at least a
total of 600 hours on both games, but in the middle of 2007, I was hit by a
GameBoy ban, which didn't end till summer 2008. By then, I totally lost
interest, and the GameBoy took its place as being a convenient paperweight and
dust collector. Never touched it again for three years.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, in 2011, some of my friends came over with their GameBoys to ask me some
Pokemon questions and how to get to Navel Rock without a GameShark. Of course,
I had lost most of my expertise on the subject, and we never got to Navel
Rock. But then, it brought back to me the fond memories of playing Pokemon,
and thinking "Hey, this is fun!". The very next day, I downloaded an emulator
and Emerald ROM, just to relive those moments.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was brilliant, playing Pokemon on that queer low-resolution and basic
pseudo-2.5D models. I couldn't care less about the life-like graphics in other
games. This was for me. I frantically hunted for my FireRed and Emerald
cartridges, but both of them were lost. Lost forever. It was a heart-breaking
moment.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after, I began trawling sites like Bulbapedia and Serebii, to catch up on
what I missed.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was an awful lot. But, looking closer, I saw a very sharp competitive edge
to the game. I was amazed, and soon after, I swallowed the concept of EVs,
IVs, and natures.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I downloaded Pokemon Platinum and DS emulator for fun. I never thought I would
actually play it. I couldn't have been more wrong. I played the whole game and
beat the Battle Frontier with all my newly-gained knowledge.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But soon, I realised, there's no way of playing with a real person like this.
So, I (nervously) asked my parents for a DS + Pokemon Black (I would've never
asked, if I hadn't got scholarship). But that was easily the best things I
could ever buy. A Cosmo Black 3DS and Pokemon Black. All I could've ever
wanted. I've played around 70 Wi-Fi battles, and won like 30 of them. I turned
to sites like &lt;a href="http://smogon.com/"&gt;Smogon&lt;/a&gt;. It was incredible, a whole
community of smart, competitive Pokemon players. It was just the place for me.
A few months ago, I became a member, and my Pokemon journey continues to
advance.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's my story. Hope you guys liked it. No Poke-Haters please!  &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Pokemon"></category><category term="Life"></category><category term="Misc"></category></entry></feed>